<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_inst">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>Click the circled image to view information about the first virus, worm, spam, and DoS attack.</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_btn1">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>First Virus</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn2">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>First Worm</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_btn3">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>First Spam</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_btn4">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>First DoS Attack</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_pop1">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>Melissa Email Virus – March, 1999 (Below is the actual email as distributed.)</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_pop2">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>The Morris Internet Worm</b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_pop3">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>First Spam on ARPAnet – 1978 (Below is the actual spam message as distributed on ARPAnet.)</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_pop4">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>Mafiaboy DoS Attack – February, 2000 (Below is an article describing the sentencing of mafiaboy shortly after conviction of the DoS attack.)</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_poptext1">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>From: ******	
Subject: Important Message From ******
To: (50 names from alias list) 

Here is that document you asked for ... don't show anyone else ;-) 

Attachment: LIST.DOC 
</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_poptext2">
	<text><![CDATA[<b>All the following events occurred on the evening of Nov. 2, 1988. 
6:00 PM - At about this time the Worm is launched. 
8:49 PM - The Worm infects a VAX 8600 at the University of Utah (cs.utah.edu). 
9:09 PM - The Worm initiates the first of its attacks to infect other computers from the infected VAX. 
9:21 PM - The load average on the system reaches 5. (Load average is a measure of how hard the computer system is working. At 9:30 at night, the load average of the VAX was usually 1. Any load average higher than 5 causes delays in data processing.) 
9:41 PM - The load average reaches 7. 
10:01 PM - The load average reaches 16. 
10:06 PM - At this point there are so many worms infecting the system that no new processes can be started. No users can use the system anymore. 
10:20 PM - The system administrator kills off the worms.
10:41 PM - The system is reinfected and the load average reaches 27. 
10:49 PM - The system administrator shuts down the system. The system is subsequently restarted.
11:21 PM - Reinfestation causes the load average to reach 37. </b>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_poptext3">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>To: Everyone
From: 
Subject: Presentation Today

DIGITAL WILL BE GIVING A PRODUCT PRESENTATION OF THE NEWEST MEMBERS OF THE DECSYSTEM-20 FAMILY; THE DECSYSTEM-2020, 2020T, 2060, AND 2060T. THE DECSYSTEM-20 FAMILY OF COMPUTERS HAS EVOLVED FROM THE TENEX OPERATING SYSTEM AND THE DECSYSTEM-10 <PDP-10> COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE. BOTH THE DECSYSTEM-2060T AND 2020T OFFER FULL ARPANET SUPPORT UNDER THE TOPS-20 OPERATING SYSTEM. THE DECSYSTEM-2060 IS AN UPWARD EXTENSION OF THE CURRENT DECSYSTEM 2040 AND 2050 FAMILY. THE DECSYSTEM-2020 IS A NEW LOW END MEMBER OF THE DECSYSTEM-20 FAMILY AND FULLY SOFTWARE COMPATIBLE WITH ALL OF THE OTHER DECSYSTEM-20 MODELS.

WE INVITE YOU TO COME SEE THE 2020 AND HEAR ABOUT THE DECSYSTEM-20 FAMILY AT THE TWO PRODUCT PRESENTATIONS WE WILL BE GIVING IN CALIFORNIA THIS MONTH. THE LOCATIONS WILL BE:

	TUESDAY, MAY 9, 1978 - 2 PM 								
	HYATT HOUSE (NEAR THE L.A. AIRPORT) 						
	LOS ANGELES, CA THURSDAY, 
	
	MAY 11, 1978 - 2 PM 									
	DUNFEY'S ROYAL COACH 							
	SAN MATEO, CA (4 MILES SOUTH OF S.F. AIRPORT AT BAYSHORE, RT 101 AND RT 92) 
	
A 2020 WILL BE THERE FOR YOU TO VIEW. ALSO TERMINALS ON-LINE TO OTHER DECSYSTEM-20 SYSTEMS THROUGH THE ARPANET. IF YOU ARE UNABLE TO ATTEND, PLEASE FEEL FREE TO CONTACT THE NEAREST DEC OFFICE FOR MORE INFORMATION ABOUT THE EXCITING DECSYSTEM-20 FAMILY. 
</b>]]></text> 
</component>

<component id="ID_poptext4">
  	<text><![CDATA[<b>'Mafiaboy' Sentenced to 8 Months
Wired News Report   09.13.01 

"Mafiaboy," the Canadian teenager who launched a denial of service attack that paralyzed many of the Internet's major sites for one week in February 2000, will be spending the next eight months in a youth detention center. 

Judge Gilles Ouellet, who presided over the trial in Quebec's Youth Court, handed down the ruling on Wednesday. 

Ouellet said that the 17-year-old had committed a criminal act when he attacked Yahoo, eBay and Amazon and other major Internet sites. 

"This is a grave matter. This attack weakened the entire electronic communication system," Ouellet told the court. "And the motivation was undeniable, this adolescent had a criminal intent." 

Prosecutor Louis Miville-Deschenes said that he hoped the sentence would send "a strong message to the hacker world." 

Mafiaboy will also serve one year of probation after his release from the detention center. During his probation he will be allowed to attend school and have a part-time job. 

He was also ordered by Ouellet to donate $250 to charity. 

Mafiaboy's real name has not been released by the court, due to the Canadian law that protects the identity of offenders under 18 years of age. 

Defense lawyer Yan Romanowski said that his client was shocked and saddened by his sentence and is considering an appeal. 

"He hoped the judge had understood that he had had his lesson and that detention was not a proper remedy in these circumstances," Romanowski said. 

"Detention is too much as far as I am concerned," Romanowski added. 

The maximum sentence Mafiaboy could have received was two years in detention. Prosecutor Louis Miville-Deschenes had asked the court to sentence Mafiaboy to one year of detention. 

"We think it is a reasonable ruling. It sends a strong message to hackers that they will get caught if they do things like that," Miville-Deschenes told reporters after court was dismissed.</b>]]></text> 
</component>

</textcomponents>