<textcomponents>

<component id="ID_title">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Message to Students</b>]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_page1">
         <text><![CDATA[page 1 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page2">
         <text><![CDATA[page 2 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page3">
         <text><![CDATA[page 3 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page4">
         <text><![CDATA[page 4 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page5">
         <text><![CDATA[page 5 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page6">
         <text><![CDATA[page 6 of 7]]></text>
</component>
<component id="ID_page7">
         <text><![CDATA[page 7 of 7]]></text>
</component>
   

<component id="ID_txt01">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Welcome</b><br/>Welcome to the CCNA Security course. The goal of this course is to develop a detailed understanding of network security principles as well as the tools and configurations available.  These online course materials will assist you in developing the skills necessary to design and support network security.]]></text>
</component>
   
<component id="ID_txt02">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>More than Just Information</b><br/>This computer-based learning environment is an important part of the overall course experience for students and instructors in the Networking Academies. These online course materials are designed to be used along with several other instructional tools and activities. These include:<br/><br/><ul><li>Class presentation, discussion and practice with your teacher</li><li>Hands-on labs that use networking equipment within the Networking Academy classroom</li><li>Online scored assessments and grade book</li><li>Packet Tracer simulation tool</li></ul>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt03">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>A Global Community</b><br/>When you participate in the Networking Academies, you are joining a global community linked by common goals and technologies. Schools in over 160 countries participate in the program. You can see an interactive network map of the global Cisco Networking Academy community at <a href="javascript:openExternal('http://www.academynetspace.com');"><font color="#0000FF">http://www.academynetspace.com</font></a>.<br/><br/>The material in this course addresses a range of technologies that facilitate how people work, live, play and learn by communicating with voice, video, and other data. We have worked with instructors around the world to create these materials. It is important that you work with your instructor and fellow students to adapt the material in this course to your local situation.<br/><br/><b>Keep in Touch</b><br />These on-line instructional materials, and the rest of the course tools, are part of the larger Cisco Networking Academy. The portal for the program is located at <a href="javascript:openExternal('http://www.cisco.com/web/learning/netacad/index.html');"><font color="#0000FF">http://www.cisco.com/web/learning/netacad/index.html</font></a>. This portal is where you access tools, informational updates and other relevant links, including the assessment server and student grade book.]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt04">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Mind Wide Open™</b><br/>An important goal in education is to enrich you, the student, by expanding what you know and can do. It is important to realize, however, that the instructional materials and the instructor can only <i>facilitate</i> the change. <i>You</i> must make the commitment yourself to learn new skills. Below are a few suggestions to help you learn:<br/><br/>1.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Take notes.</b> Professionals in the networking field often keep Engineering Journals in which they write down the things they observe and learn. Taking notes is an important way to help your understanding improve over time.</textformat><br/><br/>2.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Think about it.</b> The course provides information both to change what you know, and what you can do. As you go through the course, ask yourself what makes sense and what doesn’t. Stop and ask questions when you are confused. Try to find out more about topics which interest you. If you are not sure why something is being taught, consider asking your instructor or a friend. Think about how the different parts of the course fit together.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt05">
         <text><![CDATA[3.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Practice.</b> Learning new skills requires practice. We believe this is so important to e-learning that we have a special name for it. We call it e-Doing. It is very important that you complete the activities in the online instructional materials and that you complete the hands-on labs and Packet Tracer activities.</textformat><br/><br/>4.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Practice again.</b> Have you ever thought you knew how to do something and then, when it was time to show it on a test or at work, you discovered you really hadn’t mastered it?  Just like learning any new skill, such as a sport, game, or language, learning a professional skill requires patience and repeated practice before you can say you have truly learned it. The on-line instructional materials in this course provide repeated practice for many skills. Take full advantage of them. Work with your instructor to create additional practice opportunities using Packet Tracer and other tools.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt06">
         <text><![CDATA[5.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Teach it.</b> Teaching a friend or colleague is often a good way to improve your own learning. To teach well, you need to work through details you may have overlooked on your first reading. Conversations about the course material with fellow students, colleagues, and the instructor can help solidify your understanding of networking concepts.</textformat><br/><br/>6.<TEXTFORMAT BLOCKINDENT='15'><b> Make changes as you go.</b> The course is designed to provide feedback through interactive activities and quizzes, the online assessment system, and through interactions with your instructor. You can use this feedback to better understand where your strengths and weaknesses are. If there is an area you are having trouble with, focus on studying or practicing more in that area. Seek feedback from your instructor and other students.</textformat>]]></text>
</component>

<component id="ID_txt07">
         <text><![CDATA[<b>Explore the World of Networking</b><br/>This version of the course includes a special tool called Packet Tracer. Packet Tracer is a networking learning tool that supports a wide range of physical and logical simulations. It also provides visualization tools to help you to understand the internal workings of a network.<br/><br/>The Packet Tracer activities included with the course consist of network simulations, games, activities, and challenges that provide a broad range of learning experiences.<br/><br/><b>Create your own worlds</b><br/>You can also use Packet Tracer to create your own experiments and networking scenarios. We hope that, over time, you consider using Packet Tracer – not only for experiencing the activities included with the course, but also to become an author, explorer, and experimenter.]]></text>
</component>


</textcomponents>


