<chapter type="" id="en2001000000">
<title><content-text>Modern Network Security Threats</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en2001000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2001000100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001000101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3973776219">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001000000/en2001000100/en2001000101/cm3973776219.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001000000/en2001000100/en2001000101/cm3973776219text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network security is now an integral part of computer networking. Network security involves protocols, technologies, devices, tools, and techniques to secure data and mitigate threats. Network security solutions emerged in the 1960s but did not mature into a comprehensive set of solutions for modern networks until the 2000s. </p> <p>Network security is largely driven by the effort to stay one step ahead of ill-intentioned hackers. Just as medical doctors attempt to prevent new illness while treating existing problems, network security professionals attempt to prevent attacks while minimizing the effects of real-time attacks. Business continuity is another major driver of network security. </p> <p>Network security organizations have been created to establish formal communities of network security professionals. These organizations set standards, encourage collaboration, and provide workforce development opportunities for security professionals. It is important for network security professionals to be aware of the resources provided by these organizations.</p> <p>The complexity of network security makes it difficult to master all it encompasses. Different organizations have created domains that subdivide the world of network security into more manageable pieces. This division allows professionals to focus on more precise areas of expertise in their training, research, and employment.</p> <p>Network security policies are created by companies and government organizations to provide a framework for employees to follow during their day-to-day work. Network security professionals at the management level are responsible for creating and maintaining the network security policy. All network security practices relate to and are guided by the network security policy.</p> <p>Just as network security is composed of domains of network security, network attacks are classified so that it is easier to learn about them and address them appropriately. Viruses, worms, and Trojan Horses are specific types of network attacks. More generally, network attacks are classified as reconnaissance, access, or Denial of Service attacks.</p> <p>Mitigating network attacks is the job of a network security professional. In this chapter, the learner masters the underlying theory of network security, which is necessary to understand before beginning an in-depth practice of network security. The methods of network attack mitigation are introduced here, and the implementation of these methods comprises the remainder of this course.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2001010000">
<title><content-text>Fundamental Principles of a Secure Network</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2001010100">
<title><content-text>Evolution of Network Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6588777611">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010101/cm6588777611.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010101/cm6588777611text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In July 2001, the Code Red worm attacked web servers globally, infecting over 350,000 hosts. The worm not only disrupted access to the infected servers, but also affected the local networks hosting the servers, making them very slow or unusable. The Code Red worm caused a Denial of Service (DoS) to millions of users.</p> <p>If the network security professionals responsible for these Code Red-infected servers had developed and implemented a security policy, security patches would have been applied in a timely manner. The Code Red worm would have been stopped and would only merit a footnote in network security history.</p> <p>Network security relates directly to an organization's business continuity. Network security breaches can disrupt e-commerce, cause the loss of business data and threaten people's privacy (with the potential legal consequences), and compromise the integrity of information. These breaches can result in lost revenue for corporations, theft of intellectual property, and lawsuits, and can even threaten public safety.</p> <p>Maintaining a secure network ensures the safety of network users and protects commercial interests. To keep a network secure requires vigilance on the part of an organization's network security professionals. Security professionals must constantly be aware of new and evolving threats and attacks to networks, and vulnerabilities of devices and applications. This information is used to adapt, develop and implement mitigation techniques. However, security of the network is ultimately the responsibility of everyone that uses it. For this reason, it is the job of the network security professional to ensure that all users receive security awareness training. Maintaining a secure, protected network provides a more stable, functional work environment for everyone.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3690178793">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010102/cm3690178793.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010102/cm3690178793text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>"Necessity is the mother of invention." This saying applies perfectly to network security. In the early days of the Internet, commercial interests were negligible. The vast majority of users were research and development experts. Early users rarely engaged in activities that would harm other users. The Internet was not a secure environment because it did not need to be.</p> <p>Early on, networking involved connecting people and machines through communications media. The job of a networker was to get devices connected to improve people's ability to communicate information and ideas. The early users of the Internet did not spend much time thinking about whether or not their online activities presented a threat to the network or to their own data.</p> <p>When the first viruses were unleashed and the first DoS attack occurred, the world began to change for networking professionals. To meet the needs of users, network professionals learned techniques to secure networks. The primary focus of many network professionals evolved from designing, building, and growing networks to securing existing networks.</p> <p>Today, the Internet is a very different network compared to its beginnings in the 1960s. The job of a network professional includes ensuring that appropriate personnel are well versed in network security tools, processes, techniques, protocols, and technologies. It is critical that network security professionals maintain a healthy paranoia to manage the constantly evolving collection of threats to networks.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4498931599">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010103/cm4498931599.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010103/cm4498931599text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As network security became an integral part of everyday operations, devices dedicated to particular network security functions emerged.</p> <p>One of the first network security tools was the intrusion detection system (IDS), first developed by SRI International in 1984. An IDS provides real-time detection of certain types of attacks while they are in progress. This detection allows network professionals to more quickly mitigate the negative impact of these attacks on network devices and users. In the late 1990s, the intrusion prevention system or sensor (IPS) began to replace the IDS solution. IPS devices enable the detection of malicious activity and have the ability to automatically block the attack in real-time. </p> <p>In addition to IDS and IPS solutions, firewalls were developed to prevent undesirable traffic from entering prescribed areas within a network, thereby providing perimeter security. In 1988, Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) created the first network firewall in the form of a packet filter. These early firewalls inspected packets to see if they matched sets of predefined rules, with the option of forwarding or dropping the packets accordingly. Packet filtering firewalls inspect each packet in isolation without examining whether a packet is part of an existing connection. In 1989, AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories developed the first stateful firewall. Like packet filtering firewalls, stateful firewalls use predefined rules for permitting or denying traffic. Unlike packet filtering firewalls, stateful firewalls keep track of established connections and determine if a packet belongs to an existing flow of data, providing greater security and more rapid processing.</p> <p>The original firewalls were software features added to existing networking devices, such as routers. Over time, several companies developed standalone, or dedicated, firewalls that enable routers and switches to offload the memory and processor intensive activity of filtering packets. For organizations that do not require a dedicated firewall, modern routers, like the Cisco Integrated Services Router (ISR), can be used as sophisticated stateful firewalls.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8454571096">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010104/cm8454571096.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010104/cm8454571096text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to dealing with threats from outside of the network, network professionals must also be prepared for threats from inside the network. Internal threats, whether intentional or accidental, can cause even greater damage than external threats because of direct access to and knowledge of the corporate network and data. Despite this fact, it has taken more than 20 years after the introduction of tools and techniques for mitigating external threats to develop mitigation tools and techniques for internal threats. </p> <p>A common scenario for a threat originating from inside the network is a disgruntled employee with some technical skills and a willingness to do harm. Most threats from within the network leverage the protocols and technologies used on the local area network (LAN) or the switched infrastructure. These internal threats basically fall into two categories: spoofing and DoS.</p> <p>Spoofing attacks are attacks in which one device attempts to pose as another by falsifying data. For example, MAC address spoofing occurs when one computer accepts data packets based on the MAC address of another computer. There are other types of spoofing attacks as well. </p> <p>DoS attacks make computer resources unavailable to intended users. Attackers use various methods to launch DoS attacks.</p> <p>As a network security professional, it is important to understand the methods designed specifically for targeting these types of threats and ensuring the security of the LAN.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010105">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8827850448">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010105/cm8827850448.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010100/en2001010105/cm8827850448text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to preventing and denying malicious traffic, network security also requires that data stay protected. Cryptography, the study and practice of hiding information, is used pervasively in modern network security. Today, each type of network communication has a corresponding protocol or technology designed to hide that communication from anyone other than the intended user.</p> <p>Wireless data can be encrypted (hidden) using various cryptography applications. The conversation between two IP phone users can be encrypted. The files on a computer can also be hidden with encryption. These are just a few examples. Cryptography can be used almost anywhere that there is data communication. In fact, the trend is toward all communication being encrypted.</p> <p>Cryptography ensures data confidentiality, which is one of the three components of information security: confidentiality, integrity, and availability. Information security deals with protecting information and information systems from unauthorized access, use, disclosure, disruption, modification, or destruction. Encryption provides confidentiality by hiding plaintext data. Data integrity, meaning that the data is preserved unaltered during any operation, is achieved by the use of hashing mechanisms. Availability, which is data accessibility, is guaranteed by network hardening mechanisms and backup systems.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001010200">
<title><content-text>Drivers for Network Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4680008677">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010201/cm4680008677.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010201/cm4680008677text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The word hackers has a variety of meanings. For many, it means Internet programmers who try to gain unauthorized access to devices on the Internet. It is also used to refer to individuals that run programs to prevent or slow network access to a large number of users, or corrupt or wipe out data on servers. But for some, the term hacker has a positive interpretation as a network professional that uses sophisticated Internet programming skills to ensure that networks are not vulnerable to attack. Good or bad, hacking is a driving force in network security.</p> <p>From a business perspective, it is important to minimize the effects of hackers with bad intentions. Businesses lose productivity when the network is slow or unresponsive. Business profits are impacted by data loss and data corruption.</p> <p>The job of a network security professional is to stay one step ahead of the hackers by attending training and workshops, participating in security organizations, subscribing to real-time feeds regarding threats, and perusing security websites on a daily basis. The network security professional must also have access to state-of-the art security tools, protocols, techniques, and technologies. Network security professionals should have many of the same traits as law enforcement professionals. They should always remain aware of malicious activities and have the skills and tools to minimize or eliminate the threats associated with those activities.</p> <p>Hacking has the unintended effect of putting network security professionals at the top when it comes to employability and compensation. However, relative to other technology professions, network security has the steepest learning curve and the greatest demand for engaging in constant professional development.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9222128977">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010202/cm9222128977.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010202/cm9222128977text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Hacking started in the 1960s with phone freaking, or phreaking, which refers to using various audio frequencies to manipulate phone systems. Phreaking began when AT&amp;T introduced automatic switches to their phone systems. The AT&amp;T phone switches used various tones, or tone dialing, to indicate different functions, such as call termination and call dialing. A few AT&amp;T customers realized that by mimicking a tone using a whistle, they could exploit the phone switches to make free long-distance calls.</p> <p>As communication systems evolved, so did hacking methods. Wardialing became popular in the 1980s with the use of computer modems. Wardialing programs automatically scanned telephone numbers within a local area, dialing each one in search of computers, bulletin board systems, and fax machines. When a phone number was found, password-cracking programs were used to gain access. </p> <p>Wardriving began in the 1990s and is still popular today. With wardriving, users gain unauthorized access to networks via wireless access points. This is accomplished using a vehicle and a wireless-enabled portable computer or PDA. Password-cracking programs are used to authenticate, if necessary, and there is even software to crack the encryption scheme required to associate to the access point.</p> <p>A number of other threats have evolved since the 1960s, including network scanning tools such as Nmap and SATAN, as well as remote system administration hacking tools such as Back Orifice. Network security professionals must be familiar with all of these tools.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3663394267">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010203/cm3663394267.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010203/cm3663394267text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Trillions of dollars are transacted over the Internet on a daily basis, and the livelihoods of millions depend on Internet commerce. For this reason, criminal laws are in place to protect individual and corporate assets. There are numerous cases of individuals who have had to face the court system due to these laws.</p> <p>The first email virus, the Melissa virus, was written by David Smith of Aberdeen, New Jersey. This virus resulted in memory overflows in Internet mail servers. David Smith was sentenced to 20 months in federal prison and a US$5,000 fine.</p> <p>Robert Morris created the first Internet worm with 99 lines of code. When the Morris Worm was released, 10% of Internet systems were brought to a halt. Robert Morris was charged and received three years probation, 400 hours of community service, and a fine of US$10,000. </p> <p>One of the most notorious Internet hackers, Kevin Mitnick, was incarcerated for four years for hacking credit card accounts in the early 1990s.</p> <p>Whether the attack is via spam, a virus, DoS, or simply breaking into accounts, when the creativity of hackers is used for malicious purposes, they often end up going to jail, paying large fines, and losing access to the very environment in which they thrive.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8951248246">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010204/cm8951248246.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010200/en2001010204/cm8951248246text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>As a result of hacker exploits, the sophistication of hacker tools, and government legislation, network security solutions developed rapidly in the 1990s. By the late 1990s, many sophisticated network security solutions had been developed for organizations to strategically deploy within their networks. With these solutions came new job opportunities and increased compensation in the field of network security.</p> <p>The annual income for a network security professional is on the high end of the scale for careers in technology because of the depth and breadth of knowledge required. Network security professionals must constantly upgrade their skill set to keep abreast of the latest threats. The challenge of gaining and maintaining the necessary knowledge often translates into a shortage of network security professionals.</p> <p>Network security professionals are responsible for maintaining data assurance for an organization and ensuring the integrity and confidentiality of information. A network security professional might be responsible for setting up firewalls and intrusion prevention systems as well as ensuring encryption of company data. Implementing enterprise authentication schemes is another important task. The job entails maintaining detailed logs of suspicious activity on the network to use for reprimanding or prosecuting violators. As a network security professional, it is also important to maintain familiarity with network security organizations. These organizations often have the latest information on threats and vulnerabilities.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001010300">
<title><content-text>Network Security Organizations</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3466626909">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010301/cm3466626909.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010301/cm3466626909text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network security professionals must collaborate with professional colleagues more frequently than most other professions. This includes attending workshops and conferences that are often affiliated with, sponsored or organized by local, national, or international technology organizations.</p> <p>Three of the more well-established network security organizations are:</p> <p><ul><li> SysAdmin, Audit, Network, Security (SANS) Institute</li><li> Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT)</li><li> International Information Systems Security Certification Consortium (pronounce (ISC)2 as "I-S-C-squared") </li></ul></p> <p>A number of other network security organizations are also important to network security professionals. InfoSysSec is a network security organization that hosts a security news portal, providing the latest breaking news pertaining to alerts, exploits, and vulnerabilities. The Mitre Corporation maintains a list of common vulnerabilities and exposures (CVE) used by prominent security organizations. FIRST is a security organization that brings together a variety of computer security incident response teams from government, commercial, and educational organizations to foster cooperation and coordination in information sharing, incident prevention and rapid reaction. Finally, the Center for Internet Security (CIS) is a non-profit enterprise that develops security configuration benchmarks through a global consensus to reduce the risk of business and e-commerce disruptions. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9487372024">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010302/cm9487372024.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010302/cm9487372024text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>SANS was established in 1989 as a cooperative research and education organization. The focus of SANS is information security training and certification. SANS develops research documents about various aspects of information security.</p> <p>A range of individuals, from auditors and network administrators to chief information security officers, share learned lessons and solutions to various challenges. At the heart of SANS are security practitioners in varied global organizations, from corporations to universities, working together to help the entire information security community.</p> <p>SANS resources are largely free upon request. This includes the popular Internet Storm Center, the Internet's early warning system; NewsBites, the weekly news digest; @RISK, the weekly vulnerability digest; flash security alerts; and more than 1,200 award-winning, original research papers.</p> <p>SANS develops security courses that can be taken to prepare for Global Information Assurance Certification (GIAC) in auditing, management, operations, legal issues, security administration, and software security. GIAC validates the skills of security professionals, ranging from entry-level information security to advanced subject areas like auditing, intrusion detection, incident handling, firewalls and perimeter protection, data forensics, hacker techniques, Windows and UNIX operating system security, and secure software and application coding.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7008309312">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010303/cm7008309312.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010303/cm7008309312text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>CERT is part of the federally funded Software Engineering Institute (SEI) at Carnegie Mellon University. CERT is chartered to work with the Internet community in detecting and resolving computer security incidents. The Morris Worm motivated the formation of CERT at the directive of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA). The CERT Coordination Center (CERT/CC) focuses on coordinating communication among experts during security emergencies to help prevent future incidents. </p> <p>CERT responds to major security incidents and analyzes product vulnerabilities. CERT works to manage changes relating to progressive intruder techniques and to the difficulty of detecting attacks and catching attackers. CERT develops and promotes the use of appropriate technology and systems management practices to resist attacks on networked systems, to limit damage, and to ensure continuity of services.</p> <p>CERT focuses on five areas: software assurance, secure systems, organizational security, coordinated response, and education and training.</p> <p>CERT disseminates information by publishing articles, research and technical reports, and papers on a variety of security topics. CERT works with the news media to raise awareness of the risks on the Internet and the steps that users can take to protect themselves. CERT works with other major technology organizations, such as FIRST and IETF, to increase the commitment to security and survivability. CERT also advises U.S. government organizations, such as the National Threat Assessment Center, the National Security Council, and the Homeland Security Council.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010304">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4336199929">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010304/cm4336199929.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010304/cm4336199929text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>(ISC)2 provides vendor-neutral education products and career services in more than 135 countries. Its membership includes 60,000 certified industry professionals worldwide.</p> <p>The mission of (ISC)2 is to make the cyber world a safe place through elevating information security to the public domain and supporting and developing information security professionals around the world.</p> <p>(ISC)2 develops and maintains the (ISC)2 Common Body of Knowledge (CBK). The CBK defines global industry standards, serving as a common framework of terms and principles that (ISC)2 credentials are based upon. The CBK allows professionals worldwide to discuss, debate, and resolve matters pertaining to the field.</p> <p>Most notably, (ISC)2 is universally recognized for its four information security certifications, including one of the most popular certifications in the network security profession, the Certified Information Systems Security Professional (CISSP). These credentials help to ensure that employers. with certified employees, maintain the safety of information assets and infrastructures.</p> <p>(ISC)2 promotes expertise in handling security threats through its education and certification programs. As a member, individuals have access to current industry information and networking opportunities unique to its network of certified information security professionals.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010305">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4507486952">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010305/cm4507486952.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010300/en2001010305/cm4507486952text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In addition to the websites of the various security organizations, one of the most useful tools for the network security professional is Really Simple Syndication (RSS) feeds.</p> <p>RSS is a family of XML-based formats used to publish frequently updated information, such as blog entries, news headlines, audio, and video. RSS uses a standardized format. An RSS feed includes complete or summarized text, plus metadata, such as publishing dates and authorships. </p> <p>RSS benefits professionals who want to subscribe to timely updates from favored websites or to aggregate feeds from many sites into one place. RSS feeds can be read using a web-based RSS reader, typically built into a web browser. The RSS reader software checks the user's subscribed feeds regularly for new updates and provides an interface to monitor and read the feeds. By using RSS, a network security professional can acquire up-to-date information on a daily basis and aggregate real-time threat information for review at any time.</p> <p>For example, the US-CERT Current Activity web page is a regularly updated summary of the most frequent, high-impact types of security incidents being reported to the US-CERT. A text-only RSS feed is available at <content-link target="http://www.us-cert.gov/current/index.rdf" type="external">http://www.us-cert.gov/current/index.rdf</content-link>. This feed reports at all hours of the day and night, with information regarding security advisories, email scams, backup vulnerabilities, malware spreading via social network sites, and other potential threats.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001010400">
<title><content-text>Domains of Network Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5548610770">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010400/en2001010401/cm5548610770.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010400/en2001010401/cm5548610770text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is vital for a network security professional to understand the drivers for network security and be familiar with the organizations dedicated to network security. It is also important to have an understanding of the various network security domains. Domains provide an organized framework to facilitate learning about network security.</p> <p>There are 12 network security domains specified by the International Organization for Standardization (ISO)/International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC). Described by ISO/IEC 17799, these 12 domains serve to organize at a high level the vast realm of information under the umbrella of network security. These domains have some significant parallels with domains defined by the CISSP certification.</p> <p>The 12 domains are intended to serve as a common basis for developing organizational security standards and effective security management practices, and to help build confidence in inter-organizational activities.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2349314963">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010400/en2001010402/cm2349314963.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010400/en2001010402/cm2349314963text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The 12 domains of network security provide a convenient separation for the elements of network security. While it is not important to memorize these 12 domains, it is important to be aware of their existence and formal declaration by the ISO. They serve as a useful reference going forward in your work as a network security professional.</p> <p>One of the most important domains is security policy. A security policy is a formal statement of the rules by which people must abide who are given access to the technology and information assets of an organization. The concept, development, and application of a security policy play a significant role in keeping an organization secure. It is the responsibility of a network security professional to weave the security policy into all aspects of business operations within an organization.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001010500">
<title><content-text>Network Security Policies</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1836531562">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010501/cm1836531562.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010501/cm1836531562text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The network security policy is a broad, end-to-end document designed to be clearly applicable to an organization's operations. The policy is used to aid in network design, convey security principles, and facilitate network deployments.</p> <p>The network security policy outlines rules for network access, determines how policies are enforced, and describes the basic architecture of the organization's network security environment. The document is generally several pages. Because of its breadth of coverage and impact, it is usually compiled by a committee. It is a complex document meant to govern items such as data access, web browsing, password usage, encryption, and email attachments. </p> <p>A security policy should keep ill-intentioned users out and have control over potentially risky users. When a policy is created, it must be understood first what services are available to which users. The network security policy establishes a hierarchy of access permissions, giving employees only the minimal access necessary to perform their work.</p> <p>The network security policy outlines what assets need to be protected and gives guidance on how it should be protected. This will then be used to determine the security devices and mitigation strategies and procedures that should be implemented on the network. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8157329382">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010502/cm8157329382.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010502/cm8157329382text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A Cisco Self-Defending Network (SDN) uses the network to identify, prevent, and adapt to threats. Unlike point-solution strategies, where products are purchased individually without consideration for which products work best together, a network-based approach is a strategic approach that meets the current challenges and evolves to address new security needs.</p> <p>A Cisco SDN begins with a strong, secure, flexible network platform from which a security solution is built. A Cisco SDN topology includes Cisco Security Manager, a MARS system, one or more IPSs, one or more firewalls, several routers, and VPN concentrators. Some of these might appear as blades in a Catalyst 6500 switch or as modules in an Integrated Services Router (ISR), perhaps even as software installed on servers or as standalone devices.</p> <p>The Cisco Integrated Security Portfolio is designed to meet the requirements and diverse deployment models of any network and any environment. Many products are available to meet these needs.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010503">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5025913680">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010503/cm5025913680.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010503/cm5025913680text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most customers do not adopt all the components of the Cisco SDN at one time. For this reason, the Cisco SDN provides products that can be deployed independently and solutions that can link these products together as confidence builds in each product and subsystem.</p> <p>Elements of a Cisco SDN approach can be integrated into a network security policy. By leveraging the Cisco SDN approach when creating and amending the security policy, it can help create a hierarchical structure to the document.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001010504">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6965846789">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010504/cm6965846789.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001010000/en2001010500/en2001010504/cm6965846789text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>While the security policy should be comprehensive, it should also be succinct enough to be usable by the technology practitioners in the organization. </p> <p>One of the most important steps in creating a policy is identifying critical assets. These can include databases, vital applications, customer and employee information, classified commercial information, shared drives, email servers, and web servers.</p> <p>A security policy is a set of objectives for the company, rules of behavior for users and administrators, and requirements for system and management that collectively ensure the security of network and computer systems in an organization. A security policy is a "living document," meaning that the document is never finished and is continuously updated as technology and employee requirements change.</p> <p>For example, an organization's employee laptops will be subject to various types of attacks, such as email viruses. A network security policy explicitly defines how frequently virus software updates and virus definition updates must be installed. Additionally, the network security policy includes guidelines for what users can and cannot do. This is normally stipulated as a formal acceptable use policy (AUP). The AUP must be as explicit as possible to avoid ambiguity or misunderstanding. For example, an AUP might list the Usenet newsgroups that are prohibited.</p> <p>A network security policy drives all the steps to be taken to secure network resources. As you move through this course, the security policy will be revisited to ensure that you understand its integral nature in a well-run organization.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2001020000">
<title><content-text>Viruses, Worms, and Trojan Horses</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2001020100">
<title><content-text>Viruses</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2597016611">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020100/en2001020101/cm2597016611.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020100/en2001020101/cm2597016611text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The primary vulnerabilities for end-user computers are virus, worm, and Trojan Horse attacks:</p> <p><ul><li> A virus is malicious software which attaches to another program to execute a specific unwanted function on a computer.</li><li> A worm executes arbitrary code and installs copies of itself in the memory of the infected computer, which then infects other hosts.</li><li> A Trojan Horse is an application written to look like something else. When a Trojan Horse is downloaded and opened, it attacks the end-user computer from within.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2433231754">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020100/en2001020102/cm2433231754.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020100/en2001020102/cm2433231754text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Traditionally, the term virus refers to an infectious organism that requires a host cell to grow and replicate. A University of Southern California student named Frederick Cohen suggested the term "computer virus" in 1983. A computer virus, referred to as a virus in the rest of this course, is a program that can copy itself and infect a computer without the knowledge of the user.</p> <p>A virus is a malicious code that is attached to legitimate programs or executable files. Most viruses require end-user activation and can lay dormant for an extended period and then activate at a specific time or date. A simple virus may install itself at the first line of code on an executable file. When activated, the virus might check the disk for other executables, so that it can infect all the files it has not yet infected. Viruses can be harmless, such as those that display a picture on the screen, or they can be destructive, such as those that modify or delete files on the hard drive. Viruses can also be programmed to mutate to avoid detection.</p>  <p>In the past, viruses were usually spread via floppy disks and computer modems. Today, most viruses are spread by USB memory sticks, CDs, DVDs, network shares, or email. Email viruses are now the most common type of virus.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001020200">
<title><content-text>Worms</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5811028496">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020201/cm5811028496.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020201/cm5811028496text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Worms</b></p> <p>Worms are a particularly dangerous type of hostile code. They replicate themselves by independently exploiting vulnerabilities in networks. Worms almost always slow down networks. </p> <p>Whereas a virus requires a host program to run, worms can run by themselves. They do not require user participation and can spread extremely fast over the network. </p> <p>Worms are responsible for some of the most devastating attacks on the Internet. For example, the SQL Slammer Worm of January 2003 slowed down global Internet traffic as a result of Denial of Service. Over 250,000 hosts were affected within 30 minutes of its release. The worm exploited a buffer overflow bug in Microsoft's SQL Server. A patch for this vulnerability was released in mid-2002, so the servers that were affected were those that did not have the update patch applied. This is a great example of why it is so important for the security policy of an organization to require timely updates and patches for operating systems and applications.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1584607928">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020202/cm1584607928.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020202/cm1584607928text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Despite the mitigation techniques that have emerged over the years, worms have continued to evolve with the Internet and still pose a threat. While worms have become more sophisticated over time, they still tend to be based on exploiting weaknesses in software applications. There are three major components to most worm attacks:</p> <p><ul><li><b>Enabling vulnerability </b>- A worm installs itself using an exploit mechanism (email attachment, executable file, Trojan Horse) on a vulnerable system.</li><li><b>Propagation mechanism </b>- After gaining access to a device, the worm replicates itself and locates new targets. </li><li><b>Payload </b>- Any malicious code that results in some action. Most often this is used to create a backdoor to the infected host. </li></ul></p> <p> </p> <p>Worms are self-contained programs that attack a system to exploit a known vulnerability. Upon successful exploitation, the worm copies itself from the attacking host to the newly exploited system and the cycle begins again.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9894511121">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020203/cm9894511121.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020200/en2001020203/cm9894511121text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When exploring the major worm and virus attacks over the past 20 years, it is noticeable that the various phases of attack methods employed by hackers are often quite similar. There are five basic phases of attack, regardless of whether a worm or virus is employed.</p> <p><ul><li><b>Probe phase - </b>Vulnerable targets are identified. The goal is to find computers that can be subverted. Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP) ping scans are used to map networks. Then the application scans and identifies operating systems and vulnerable software. Hackers can obtain passwords using social engineering, dictionary attack, brute-force attack, or network sniffing.</li><li><b>Penetrate phase </b>- Exploit code is transferred to the vulnerable target. The goal is to get the target to execute the exploit code through an attack vector, such as a buffer overflow, ActiveX or Common Gateway Interface (CGI) vulnerabilities, or an email virus.</li><li><b>Persist phase </b>- After the attack is successfully launched in the memory, the code tries to persist on the target system. The goal is to ensure that the attacker code is running and available to the attacker even if the system reboots. This is achieved by modifying system files, making registry changes, and installing new code.</li><li><b>Propagate phase </b>- The attacker attempts to extend the attack to other targets by looking for vulnerable neighboring machines. Propagation vectors include emailing copies of the attack to other systems, uploading files to other systems using file shares or FTP services, active web connections, and file transfers through Internet Relay Chat (IRC).</li><li><b>Paralyze phase </b>- Actual damage is done to the system. Files can be erased, systems can crash, information can be stolen, and distributed DoS (DDoS) attacks can be launched.</li></ul></p> <p>The five basic phases of attack allow security experts to conveniently describe worms and viruses according to their particular implementation mechanism for each phase. This makes it easier to categorize worms and viruses.</p> <p>Viruses and worms are two methods of attack. Another method is the Trojan Horse, which leverages viruses or worms with the added element of masquerading as a benign program.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001020300">
<title><content-text>Trojan Horses</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3025286547">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020300/en2001020301/cm3025286547.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020300/en2001020301/cm3025286547text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Trojan Horse</b></p> <p>The term Trojan Horse originated from Greek mythology. Greek warriors offered the people of Troy (Trojans) a giant hollow horse as a gift. The Trojans brought the giant horse into their walled city, unaware that it contained many Greek warriors. At night, after most Trojans were asleep, the warriors burst out of the horse and overtook the city.</p> <p>A Trojan Horse in the world of computing is malware that carries out malicious operations under the guise of a desired function. A virus or worm could carry a Trojan Horse. A Trojan Horse contains hidden, malicious code that exploits the privileges of the user that runs it. Games can often have a Trojan Horse attached to them. When running the game, the game works, but in the background, the Trojan Horse has been installed on the user's system and continues running after the game has been closed.</p> <p>The Trojan Horse concept is flexible. It can cause immediate damage, provide remote access to the system (a back door), or perform actions as instructed remotely, such as "send me the password file once per week." </p> <p>Custom-written Trojan Horses, such as Trojan Horses with a specific target, are difficult to detect.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4448482897">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020300/en2001020302/cm4448482897.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020300/en2001020302/cm4448482897text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Trojan Horses are usually classified according to the damage that they cause or the manner in which they breach a system:</p> <p><ul><li>Remote-access Trojan Horse (enables unauthorized remote access)</li><li>Data sending Trojan Horse (provides the attacker with sensitive data such as passwords)</li><li>Destructive Trojan Horse (corrupts or deletes files)</li><li>Proxy Trojan Horse (user's computer functions as a proxy server)</li><li>FTP Trojan Horse (opens port 21)</li><li>Security software disabler Trojan Horse (stops anti-virus programs or firewalls from functioning)</li><li>Denial of Service Trojan Horse (slows or halts network activity)</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001020400">
<title><content-text>Mitigating Viruses, Worms, and Trojan Horses</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9224966508">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020401/cm9224966508.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020401/cm9224966508text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A majority of the software vulnerabilities that are discovered relate to buffer overflows. A buffer is an allocated area of memory used by processes to store data temporarily. A buffer overflow occurs when a fixed-length buffer reaches its capacity and a process attempts to store data above and beyond that maximum limit. This can result in extra data overwriting adjacent memory locations as well as cause other unexpected behavior. Buffer overflows are usually the primary conduit through which viruses, worms, and Trojan Horses do their damage. In fact, there are reports that suggest that one-third of the software vulnerabilities identified by CERT relate to buffer overflows.</p> <p>Viruses and Trojan Horses tend to take advantage of local root buffer overflows. A root buffer overflow is a buffer overflow intended to attain root privileges to a system. Local root buffer overflows require the end user or system to take some type of action. A local root buffer overflow is typically initiated by a user opening an email attachment, visiting a website, or exchanging a file via instant messaging.</p> <p>Worms such as SQL Slammer and Code Red exploit remote root buffer overflows. Remote root buffer overflows are similar to local root buffer overflows, except that local end user or system intervention is not required.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7136454944">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020402/cm7136454944.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020402/cm7136454944text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Viruses, worms, and Trojan horses can cause serious problems on networks and end systems. Network administrators have several means of mitigating these attacks. Note that mitigation techniques are often referred to in the security community as countermeasures.</p>  <p>The primary means of mitigating virus and Trojan horse attacks is anti-virus software. Anti-virus software helps prevent hosts from getting infected and spreading malicious code. It requires much more time to clean up infected computers than it does to maintain up-to-date anti-virus software and anti-virus definitions on the same machines. </p> <p>Anti-virus software is the most widely deployed security product on the market today. Several companies that create anti-virus software, such as Symantec, Computer Associates, McAfee, and Trend Micro, have been in the business of detecting and eliminating viruses for more than a decade. Many corporations and educational institutions purchase volume licensing for their users. The users are able to log in to a website with their account and download the anti-virus software on their desktops, laptops, or servers.</p> <p>Anti-virus products have update automation options so that new virus definitions and new software updates can be downloaded automatically or on demand. This practice is the most critical requirement for keeping a network free of viruses and should be formalized in a network security policy.</p> <p>Anti-virus products are host-based. These products are installed on computers and servers to detect and eliminate viruses. However, they do not prevent viruses from entering the network, so a network security professional needs to be aware of the major viruses and keep track of security updates regarding emerging viruses.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1091305219">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020403/cm1091305219.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020403/cm1091305219text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Worms are more network-based than viruses. Worm mitigation requires diligence and coordination on the part of network security professionals. The response to a worm infection can be broken down into four phases: containment, inoculation, quarantine, and treatment. </p> <p>The containment phase involves limiting the spread of a worm infection to areas of the network that are already affected. This requires compartmentalization and segmentation of the network to slow down or stop the worm and prevent currently infected hosts from targeting and infecting other systems. Containment requires using both outgoing and incoming ACLs on routers and firewalls at control points within the network.</p> <p>The inoculation phase runs parallel to or subsequent to the containment phase. During the inoculation phase, all uninfected systems are patched with the appropriate vendor patch for the vulnerability. The inoculation process further deprives the worm of any available targets. A network scanner can help identify potentially vulnerable hosts. The mobile environment prevalent on modern networks poses significant challenges. Laptops are routinely taken out of the secure network environment and connected to potentially unsecure environments, such as home networks. Without proper patching of the system, a laptop can be infected with a worm or virus and then bring it back into the secure environment of the organization's network where it can infect other systems.</p> <p>The quarantine phase involves tracking down and identifying infected machines within the contained areas and disconnecting, blocking, or removing them. This isolates these systems appropriately for the treatment phase.</p> <p>During the treatment phase, actively infected systems are disinfected of the worm. This can involve terminating the worm process, removing modified files or system settings that the worm introduced, and patching the vulnerability the worm used to exploit the system. Or, in more severe cases, can require completely reinstalling the system to ensure that the worm and its byproducts are removed.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020404">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5490964464">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020404/cm5490964464.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020404/cm5490964464text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In the case of the SQL Slammer worm, malicious traffic was detected on UDP port 1434. This port should normally be blocked by a firewall on the perimeter. However, most infections enter by way of back doors and do not pass through the firewall; therefore, to prevent the spreading of this worm it would be necessary to block this port on all devices throughout the internal network. </p> <p>In some cases, the port on which the worm is spreading might be critical to business operation. For example, when SQL Slammer was propagating, some organizations could not block UDP port 1434 because it was required to access the SQL Server for legitimate business transactions. In such a situation, alternatives must be considered.</p> <p>If the network devices using the service on the affected port are known, permitting selective access is an option. For example, if only a small number of clients are using SQL Server, one option is to open UDP port 1434 to critical devices only. Selective access is not guaranteed to solve the problem, but it certainly lowers the probability of infection.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001020405">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1192662876">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020405/cm1192662876.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001020000/en2001020400/en2001020405/cm1192662876text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A comprehensive option for mitigating the effects of viruses, worms, and Trojan Horses is a host-based intrusion prevention system (HIPS). </p> <p>Cisco Security Agent (CSA) is a host-based intrusion prevention system that can be integrated with anti-virus software from various vendors. CSA protects the operating system from threats on the network. CSA provides a more comprehensive and centralized solution that is not dependent on end users being vigilant about updating anti-virus software and using host-based firewalls.</p> <p>Another solution for mitigating threats is Cisco Network Admission Control (NAC). The Cisco NAC Appliance is a turnkey solution to control network access. It admits only hosts that are authenticated and have had their security posture examined and approved for the network. This solution is a natural fit for organizations with medium-sized networks that need simplified, integrated tracking of operating systems, anti-virus patches, and vulnerability updates. The Cisco NAC Appliance does not need to be part of a Cisco network to function. </p> <p>Cisco Security Monitoring, Analysis, and Response System (MARS) provides security monitoring for network security devices and host applications made by Cisco and other providers. MARS makes precise recommendations for threat removal, including the ability to visualize the attack path and identify the source of the threat with detailed topological graphs that simplify security response.</p> <p>Viruses, worms, and Trojan Horses can slow or stop networks and corrupt or destroy data. Software and hardware options are available for mitigating these threats. Network security professionals must maintain constant vigilance. It is not enough just to react to threats. A good network security professional examines the whole network to find vulnerabilities and fix them before an attack occurs.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2001030000">
<title><content-text>Attack Methodologies</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2001030100">
<title><content-text>Reconnaissance Attacks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8657455805">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030101/cm8657455805.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030101/cm8657455805text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are many different types of network attacks other than viruses, worms, and Trojan Horses. To mitigate attacks, it is useful to first have the various types of attacks categorized. By categorizing network attacks, it is possible to address types of attacks rather than individual attacks. There is no standardized way of categorizing network attacks. The method used in this course classifies attacks in three major categories.</p> <p><b>Reconnaissance Attacks</b></p> <p>Reconnaissance attacks involve the unauthorized discovery and mapping of systems, services, or vulnerabilities. Reconnaissance attacks often employ the use of packet sniffers and port scanners, which are widely available as free downloads on the Internet. Reconnaissance is analogous to a thief surveying a neighborhood for vulnerable homes to break into, such as an unoccupied residence or a house with an easy-to-open door or window.</p> <p><b>Access Attacks</b></p> <p>Access attacks exploit known vulnerabilities in authentication services, FTP services, and web services to gain entry to web accounts, confidential databases, and other sensitive information. An access attack can be performed in many different ways. An access attack often employs a dictionary attack to guess system passwords. </p> <p><b>Denial of Service Attacks</b> </p> <p>Denial of service attacks send extremely large numbers of requests over a network or the Internet. These excessive requests cause the target device to run suboptimally. Consequently, the attacked device becomes unavailable for legitimate access and use. By executing exploits or combinations of exploits, DoS attacks slow or crash applications and processes.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4765841667">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030102/cm4765841667.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030102/cm4765841667text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Reconnaissance attacks</b> </p> <p>Reconnaissance is also known as information gathering and, in most cases, precedes an access or DoS attack. In a reconnaissance attack, the malicious intruder typically begins by conducting a ping sweep of the target network to determine which IP addresses are active. The intruder then determines which services or ports are available on the live IP addresses. Nmap is the most popular application for performing port scans. From the port information obtained, the intruder queries the ports to determine the type and version of the application and operating system that is running on the target host. In many cases, the intruders look for vulnerable services that can be exploited later when there is less likelihood of being caught.</p> <p>Reconnaissance attacks use various tools to gain access to a network:</p> <p><ul><li>Packet sniffers</li><li>Ping sweeps</li><li>Port scans</li><li>Internet information queries</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9839228364">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030103/cm9839228364.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030103/cm9839228364text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A packet sniffer is a software application that uses a network adapter card in promiscuous mode to capture all network packets that are sent across a LAN. Promiscuous mode is a mode in which the network adapter card sends all packets that are received to an application for processing. Some network applications distribute network packets in unencrypted plaintext. Because the network packets are not encrypted, they can be understood by any application that can pick them off the network and process them.</p> <p>Packet sniffers can only work in the same collision domain as the network being attacked, unless the attacker has access to the intermediary switches.</p> <p>Numerous freeware and shareware packet sniffers, such as Wireshark, are available and do not require the user to understand anything about the underlying protocols.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3953528669">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030104/cm3953528669.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030104/cm3953528669text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When used as legitimate tools, ping sweep and port scan applications run a series of tests against hosts and devices to identify vulnerable services. The information is gathered by examining IP addressing and port, or banner, data from both TCP and UDP ports. An attacker uses ping sweeps and port scans to acquire information to compromise the system.</p> <p>A ping sweep is a basic network scanning technique that determines which range of IP addresses map to live hosts. A single ping indicates whether one specified host computer exists on the network. A ping sweep consists of ICMP echo requests sent to multiple hosts. If a given address is live, the address returns an ICMP echo reply. Ping sweeps are among the older and slower methods used to scan a network. </p> <p>Each service on a host is associated with a well-known port number. Port scanning is a scan of a range of TCP or UDP port numbers on a host to detect listening services. It consists of sending a message to each port on a host. The response that the sender receives indicates whether the port is used.</p> <p>Internet information queries can reveal information such as who owns a particular domain and what addresses have been assigned to that domain. They can also reveal who owns a particular IP address and which domain is associated with the address. </p> <p>Ping sweeps of addresses revealed by Internet information queries can present a picture of the live hosts in a particular environment. After such a list is generated, port scanning tools can cycle through all well-known ports to provide a complete list of all services that are running on the hosts that the ping sweep discovered. Hackers can then examine the characteristics of active applications, which can lead to specific information that is useful to a hacker whose intent is to compromise that service.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030105">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4126002510">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030105/cm4126002510.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030100/en2001030105/cm4126002510text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Keep in mind that reconnaissance attacks are typically the precursor to further attacks with the intention of gaining unauthorized access to a network or disrupting network functionality. A network security professional can detect when a reconnaissance attack is underway by configured alarms that are triggered when certain parameters are exceeded, such as ICMP requests per second. A Cisco ISR supports the security technologies that enable these types of alarms to be triggered. This is made available by the network-based intrusion prevention functionality supported by Cisco IOS security images running on ISRs.</p> <p>Host-based intrusion prevention systems and standalone network-based intrusion detection systems can also be used to notify when a reconnaissance attack is occurring.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001030200">
<title><content-text>Access Attacks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8869603135">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030201/cm8869603135.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030201/cm8869603135text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Access attacks</b></p> <p>Hackers use access attacks on networks or systems for three reasons: retrieve data, gain access, and escalate access privileges. </p> <p>Access attacks often employ password attacks to guess system passwords. Password attacks can be implemented using several methods, including brute-force attacks, Trojan Horse programs, IP spoofing, and packet sniffers. However, most password attacks refer to brute-force attacks, which involve repeated attempts based on a built-in dictionary to identify a user account or password. </p> <p>A brute-force attack is often performed using a program that runs across the network and attempts to log in to a shared resource, such as a server. After an attacker gains access to a resource, the attacker has the same access rights as the user whose account was compromised. If this account has sufficient privileges, the attacker can create a back door for future access without concern for any status and password changes to the compromised user account.</p> <p>As an example, a user can run the L0phtCrack, or LC5, application to perform a brute-force attack to obtain a Windows server password. When the password is obtained, the attacker can install a keylogger, which sends a copy of all keystrokes to a desired destination. Or, a Trojan Horse can be installed to send a copy of all packets sent and received by the target to a particular destination, thus enabling the monitoring of all the traffic to and from that server.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8669894128">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030202/cm8669894128.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030202/cm8669894128text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are five types of access attacks:</p> <p><ul><li><b>Password attack </b>- An attacker attempts to guess system passwords. A common example is a dictionary attack.</li><li><b>Trust exploitation </b>- An attacker uses privileges granted to a system in an unauthorized way, possibly leading to compromising the target.</li><li><b>Port redirection </b>- A compromised system is used as a jump-off point for attacks against other targets. An intrusion tool is installed on the compromised system for session redirection.</li><li><b>Man-in-the-middle attack </b>- An attacker is positioned in the middle of communications between two legitimate entities in order to read or modify the data that passes between the two parties. A popular man-in-the-middle attack involves a laptop acting as a rogue access point to capture and copy all network traffic from a targeted user. Often the user is in a public location on a wireless hotspot.</li><li><b>Buffer overflow </b>- A program writes data beyond the allocated buffer memory. Buffer overflows usually arise as a consequence of a bug in a C or C++ program. A result of the overflow is that valid data is overwritten or exploited to enable the execution of malicious code.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1758465312">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030203/cm1758465312.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030200/en2001030203/cm1758465312text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Access attacks in general can be detected by reviewing logs, bandwidth utilization, and process loads.</p> <p>The network security policy should specify that logs are formally maintained for all network devices and servers. By reviewing logs, security personnel can determine if an unusual number of failed login attempts have occurred. Software packages such as ManageEngine EventLog Analyzer or Cisco Secure Access Control Server (CSACS) maintain information regarding failed login attempts to network devices. UNIX and Windows servers also keep a log of failed login attempts. Cisco routers and firewall devices can be configured to prevent login attempts for a given time from a particular source after a prescribed number of failures in a specified amount of time.</p> <p>Man-in-the-middle attacks often involve replicating data. An indication of such an attack is an unusual amount of network activity and bandwidth utilization, as indicated by network monitoring software. </p> <p>Similarly, an access attack resulting in a compromised system would likely be revealed by sluggish activity due to ongoing buffer overflow attacks, as indicated by active process loads viewable on a Windows or UNIX system.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001030300">
<title><content-text>Denial of Service Attacks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4019353476">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030301/cm4019353476.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030301/cm4019353476text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Denial of Service Attacks</b></p> <p>A DoS attack is a network attack that results in some sort of interruption of service to users, devices, or applications. Several mechanisms can generate a DoS attack. The simplest method is to generate large amounts of what appears to be valid network traffic. This type of network DoS attack saturates the network so that valid user traffic cannot get through. </p> <p>A DoS attack takes advantage of the fact that target systems such as servers must maintain state information. Applications may rely on expected buffer sizes and specific content of network packets. A DoS attack can exploit this by sending packet sizes or data values that are not expected by the receiving application.</p> <p>There are two major reasons a DoS attack occurs: </p> <p><ul><li>A host or application fails to handle an unexpected condition, such as maliciously formatted input data, an unexpected interaction of system components, or simple resource exhaustion. </li><li>A network, host, or application is unable to handle an enormous quantity of data, causing the system to crash or become extremely slow.</li></ul></p> <p>DoS attacks attempt to compromise the availability of a network, host, or application. They are considered a major risk because they can easily interrupt a business process and cause significant loss. These attacks are relatively simple to conduct, even by an unskilled attacker.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4193915960">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030302/cm4193915960.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030302/cm4193915960text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One example of a DoS attack is sending a poisonous packet. A poisonous packet is an improperly formatted packet designed to cause the receiving device to process the packet in an improper fashion. The poisonous packet causes the receiving device to crash or run very slowly. This attack can cause all communications to and from the device to be disrupted.</p> <p>In another example, an attacker sends a continuous stream of packets, which overwhelms the available bandwidth of network links. In most cases, it is impossible to differentiate between the attacker and legitimate traffic and to trace an attack quickly back to its source. If many systems in the Internet core are compromised, the attacker may be able to take advantage of virtually unlimited bandwidth to unleash packet storms toward desired targets. </p> <p>A Distributed Denial of Service Attack (DDoS) is similar in intent to a DoS attack, except that a DDoS attack originates from multiple coordinated sources. In addition to increasing the amount of network traffic from multiple distributed attackers, a DDoS attack also presents the challenge of requiring the network defense to identify and stop each distributed attacker.</p> <p>As an example, a DDoS attack could proceed as follows. A hacker scans for systems that are accessible. After the hacker accesses several "handler" systems, the hacker installs zombie software on them. Zombies then scan and infect agent systems. When the hacker accesses the agent systems, the hacker loads remote-control attack software to carry out the DDoS attack.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2144248886">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030303/cm2144248886.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030303/cm2144248886text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is useful to detail three common DoS attacks to get a better understanding of how DoS attacks work.</p> <p><b>Ping of Death</b></p> <p>In a ping of death attack, a hacker sends an echo request in an IP packet larger than the maximum packet size of 65,535 bytes. Sending a ping of this size can crash the target computer. A variant of this attack is to crash a system by sending ICMP fragments, which fill the reassembly buffers of the target.</p> <p><b>Smurf Attack</b></p> <p>In a smurf attack, a perpetrator sends a large number of ICMP requests to directed broadcast addresses, all with spoofed source addresses on the same network as the respective directed broadcast. If the routing device delivering traffic to those broadcast addresses forwards the directed broadcasts, all hosts on the destination networks send ICMP replies, multiplying the traffic by the number of hosts on the networks. On a multi-access broadcast network, hundreds of machines might reply to each packet.</p> <p><b>TCP SYN Flood</b></p> <p>In a TCP SYN flood attack, a flood of TCP SYN packets is sent, often with a forged sender address. Each packet is handled like a connection request, causing the server to spawn a half-open connection by sending back a TCP SYN-ACK packet and waiting for a packet in response from the sender address. However, because the sender address is forged, the response never comes. These half-open connections saturate the number of available connections the server is able to make, keeping it from responding to legitimate requests until after the attack ends.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030304">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2008319112">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030304/cm2008319112.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030300/en2001030304/cm2008319112text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The TCP SYN flood, ping of death, and smurf attacks demonstrate how devastating a DoS attack can be. To date, hundreds of DoS attacks have been documented. There are five basic ways that DoS attacks can do harm:</p> <p><ul><li>Consumption of computational resources, such as bandwidth, disk space, or processor time</li><li>Disruption of configuration information, such as routing information</li><li>Disruption of state information, such as unsolicited resetting of TCP sessions</li><li>Disruption of physical network components</li><li>Obstruction of communication between the victim and others.</li></ul></p> <p>It is usually not difficult to determine if a DoS attack is occurring. A large number of complaints about not being able to access resources is a first sign of a DoS attack. To minimize the number of attacks, a network utilization software package should be running at all times, which should also be required by the network security policy. A network utilization graph showing unusual activity could indicate a DoS attack.</p> <p>Keep in mind that DoS attacks could be a component of a larger offensive. DoS attacks can lead to problems in the network segments of the computers being attacked. For example, the packet-per-second capacity of a router between the Internet and a LAN might be exceeded by an attack, compromising not only the target system but also the entire network. If the attack is conducted on a sufficiently large scale, entire geographical regions of Internet connectivity could be compromised.</p> <p>Not all service outages, even those that result from malicious activity, are necessarily DoS attacks. In any case, DoS attacks are among the most dangerous types of attacks, and it is critical that a network security professional act quickly to mitigate the effects of such attacks.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2001030400">
<title><content-text>Mitigating Network Attacks</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4324418681">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030401/cm4324418681.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030401/cm4324418681text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are a variety of network attacks, network attack methodologies, and categorizations of network attacks. The important question is, 'How do I mitigate these network attacks?'</p> <p>The type of attack, as specified by the categorization of reconnaissance, access, or DoS attack, determines the means of mitigating a network threat.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7578407965">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030402/cm7578407965.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030402/cm7578407965text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Reconnaissance attacks can be mitigated in several ways.</p> <p>Using strong authentication is a first option for defense against packet sniffers. Strong authentication is a method of authenticating users that cannot easily be circumvented. A One-Time Password (OTP) is a form of strong authentication. OTPs utilize two-factor authentication. Two-factor authentication combines something one has, such as a token card, with something one knows, such as a PIN. Automated teller machines (ATMs) use two-factor authentication.</p> <p>Encryption is also effective for mitigating packet sniffer attacks. If traffic is encrypted, it is practically irrelevant if a packet sniffer is being used because the captured data is not readable. </p> <p>Antisniffer software and hardware tools detect changes in the response time of hosts to determine whether the hosts are processing more traffic than their own traffic loads would indicate. While this does not completely eliminate the threat, as part of an overall mitigation system, it can reduce the number of instances of threat. </p> <p>A switched infrastructure is the norm today, which makes it difficult to capture any data except that on your immediate collision domain, which probably contains only one host. A switched infrastructure does not eliminate the threat of packet sniffers, but can greatly reduce the sniffer's effectiveness.</p> <p>It is impossible to mitigate port scanning. But using an IPS and firewall can limit the information that can be discovered with a port scanner. Ping sweeps can be stopped if ICMP echo and echo-reply are turned off on edge routers. However, when these services are turned off, network diagnostic data is lost. Additionally, port scans can be run without full ping sweeps. The scans simply take longer because IP addresses that are not live are also scanned.</p> <p>Network-based IPS and host-based IPS can usually notify an administrator when a reconnaissance attack is under way. This warning enables the administrator to better prepare for the coming attack or to notify the ISP from where the reconnaissance probe is launching from.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030403">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6983237613">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030403/cm6983237613.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030403/cm6983237613text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Several techniques are also available for mitigating access attacks.</p> <p>A surprising number of access attacks are carried out through simple password guessing or brute-force dictionary attacks against passwords. The use of encrypted or hashed authentication protocols, along with a strong password policy, greatly reduces the probability of successful access attacks. There are specific practices that help to ensure a strong password policy: </p> <p><ul><li>Disabling accounts after a specific number of unsuccessful logins. This practice helps to prevent continuous password attempts.</li><li>Not using plaintext passwords. Use either a one-time password (OTP) or encrypted password.</li><li>Using strong passwords. Strong passwords are at least eight characters and contain uppercase letters, lowercase letters, numbers, and special characters. </li></ul></p> <p>The principle of minimum trust should also be designed into the network structure. This means that systems should not use one another unnecessarily. For example, if an organization has a server that is used by untrusted devices, such as web servers, the trusted device (server) should not trust the untrusted devices (web servers) unconditionally.</p> <p>Cryptography is a critical component of any modern secure network. Using encryption for remote access to a network is recommended. Also, routing protocol traffic should be encrypted as well. The more that traffic is encrypted, the less opportunity hackers have for intercepting data with man-in-the-middle attacks.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030404">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2259906904">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030404/cm2259906904.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030404/cm2259906904text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Companies with a high-profile Internet presence should plan in advance how to respond to potential DoS attacks. Historically, many DoS attacks were sourced from spoofed source addresses. These types of attacks can be thwarted using antispoofing technologies on perimeter routers and firewalls. Many DoS attacks today are distributed DoS attacks carried out by compromised hosts on several networks. Mitigating DDoS attacks requires careful diagnostics, planning, and cooperation from ISPs.</p> <p>The most important elements for mitigating DoS attacks are firewalls and IPSs. Both host-based and network-based IPSs are strongly recommended.</p> <p>Cisco routers and switches support a number of antispoofing technologies, such as port security, DHCP snooping, IP Source Guard, Dynamic ARP Inspection, and ACLs.</p> <p>Lastly, although Quality of Service (QoS) is not designed as a security technology, one of its applications, traffic policing, can be used to limit ingress traffic from any given customer on an edge router. This limits the impact a single source can have on ingress bandwidth utilization.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2001030405">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2970723508">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030405/cm2970723508.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001030000/en2001030400/en2001030405/cm2970723508text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Defending your network against attack requires constant vigilance and education. There are 10 best practices that represent the best insurance for your network.</p> <p><b>1.</b> Keep patches up to date by installing them weekly or daily, if possible, to prevent buffer overflow and privilege escalation attacks.</p> <p><b>2.</b> Shut down unnecessary services and ports.</p> <p><b>3.</b> Use strong passwords and change them often.</p> <p><b>4.</b> Control physical access to systems.</p> <p><b>5.</b> Avoid unnecessary web page inputs. Some websites allow users to enter usernames and passwords. A hacker can enter more than just a username. For example, entering "jdoe; rm -rf /" might allow an attacker to remove the root file system from a UNIX server. Programmers should limit input characters and not accept invalid characters such as | ; &lt; > as input.</p> <p><b>6.</b> Perform backups and test the backed up files on a regular basis.</p> <p><b>7.</b> Educate employees about the risks of social engineering, and develop strategies to validate identities over the phone, via email, or in person.</p> <p><b>8.</b> Encrypt and password-protect sensitive data.</p> <p><b>9.</b> Implement security hardware and software such as firewalls, IPSs, virtual private network (VPN) devices, anti-virus software, and content filtering.</p> <p><b>10.</b> Develop a written security policy for the company.</p> <p>These methods are only a starting point for sound security management. Organizations must remain vigilant at all times to defend against continually evolving threats.</p> <p>Using these proven methods of securing a network and applying the knowledge gained in this chapter, you are now prepared to begin deploying network security solutions. One of the first deployment considerations involves securing access to network devices. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en2001040000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2001040100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en2001040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7123654100">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2001000000/en2001040000/en2001040100/en2001040101/cm7123654100.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2001000000/en2001040000/en2001040100/en2001040101/cm7123654100text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
