<chapter type="" id="en2009000000">
<title><content-text>Managing a Secure Network</content-text></title>
<section type="ChapterIntroduction" id="en2009000000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009000100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Introduction</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009000101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3796019166">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009000000/en2009000100/en2009000101/cm3796019166.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009000000/en2009000100/en2009000101/cm3796019166text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Mitigating network attacks requires a comprehensive, end-to-end approach that includes creating and maintaining security policies based on the security needs of an organization. The first step in establishing an organization's security needs is to identify likely threats and perform a risk analysis, the results of which are used to establish the security hardware and software implementations, mitigation policies, and network design. </p> <p>To help simplify network design, it is recommended that all security mechanisms come from a single vendor. The Cisco Self-Defending Network is a comprehensive, end-to-end solution for network security. Cisco Security Manager and Cisco MARS provide network management options for Cisco SDN solutions. </p> <p>After the network is designed, operations security entails the day-to-day practices necessary to first deploy and later maintain the secure system. Part of maintaining a secure system is network security testing. Security testing is performed by the operations team, to ensure that all security implementations are operating as expected. Testing is also used to provide insight into business continuity planning, which addresses the continuing operations of an organization in the event of a disaster, disruption, or prolonged service interruption. </p> <p>After a secure network is implemented and continuity plans are established, those plans and documents must be continuously updated based on the changing needs of the organization. For this reason, it is necessary to understand the system development life cycle (SDLC) for the purposes of evaluating system changes and adjusting security implementations. The SDLC includes five phases: initiation, acquisition and development, implementation, operations and maintenance, and disposition. It is important to include security considerations in all phases of the SDLC.</p> <p>A network security system cannot completely prevent assets from being vulnerable to threats. New attacks are developed and vulnerabilities identified that can be used to circumvent security solutions. Additionally, technical, administrative, and physical security systems can be defeated if the end user community does not adhere to security practices and procedures. A comprehensive security policy must be maintained which identifies an organization's assets, specifies the security hardware and software requirements for protecting those assets, clarifies the roles and responsibilities of personnel, and establishes the proper protocol for responding to security breaches. If security policies are established and followed, organizations can minimize the loss and damages resulting from attacks.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009010000">
<title><content-text>Principles of Secure Network Design</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009010100">
<title><content-text>Ensuring a Network is Secure</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7329262091">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010100/en2009010101/cm7329262091.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010100/en2009010101/cm7329262091text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Mitigating network attacks requires a comprehensive, end-to-end approach:</p> <p><ul><li> Secure network devices with AAA, SSH, role-based CLI, syslog, SNMP, and NTP. </li><li> Secure services using AutoSecure and one-step lockdown. </li><li> Protect network endpoints, such as workstations and servers, against viruses, Trojan Horses, and worms with Cisco NAC, Cisco IronPort, and Cisco Security Agent. </li><li> Use Cisco IOS Firewall and accompanying ACLs to secure resources internally while protecting those resources from outside attacks. </li><li> Supplement Cisco IOS Firewall with Cisco IPS technology to evaluate traffic using an attack signature database. </li><li> Protect the LAN by following Layer 2 and VLAN recommended practices and by using a variety of technologies, including BPDU guard, root guard, PortFast, and SPAN. </li></ul></p> <p>Despite these security techniques, hackers are continuously developing new ways to attack networks. An important part of implementing a secure network is creating and maintaining security policies to mitigate existing as well as new kinds of attacks. These polices enforce a structured, informed, consistent approach to securing the network. When developing security policies, several questions must be answered: </p> <p><ul><li><b>Business needs</b> - What does the organization want to do with the network? What are the organizational needs? Regardless of the security implications, business needs must come first.</li><li><b>Threat Identification</b> - What are the most likely types of threats given the organization's purpose? For example, a financial institution will face different threats than a university. </li><li><b>Risk analysis</b> - What is the cost versus benefit analysis of implementing various security technologies? How do the latest security techniques affect the network environment and what is the risk if they are not implemented? </li><li><b>Security needs</b> - What are the policies, standards, and guidelines needed to address business needs and risks?</li><li><b>Industry-recommended practices</b> - What are the reliable, well-understood, and recommended security practices that similar organizations currently employ?</li><li><b>Security operations</b> - What are the current procedures for incident response, monitoring, maintenance, and auditing of the system for compliance?</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9507671156">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010100/en2009010102/cm9507671156.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010100/en2009010102/cm9507671156text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Many security assumptions are made when designing and implementing a secure network. Unfortunately, unfounded assumptions about how and where the system will be used can lead to broken, misconfigured, or bypassed security mechanisms. An example of a bad assumption is that more users need to use a protocol, such as FTP, than is actually the case.</p> <p>A wrong assumption has negative ramifications for all design work. It might influence one design decision, and then propagate to other decisions that depend on it. Wrong decisions are especially dangerous in early stages of secure system design when threats are modeled and risks are assessed. It is often easy to correct or enhance a single implementation aspect of a system, such as a firewall configuration. However, design errors, such as where that firewall is placed, are either extremely hard or impossible to correct without substantial investments in time and technology.</p> <p>There are guidelines to help you avoid making wrong assumptions:</p> <p><ul><li>Expect that any aspect of a security system might fail. When designing a system, perform what-if analysis for failures of every element, assess the probability of failure, and analyze all possible consequences of a failure, taking into account cascading failures of other elements.</li><li>Identify any elements that fail-open. Fail-open occurs when a failure results in a complete bypass of the security function. Ideally, any security element should be fail-safe. If the element fails, it should default to a secure state, such as blocking all traffic.</li><li>Try to identify all attack possibilities. One way to accomplish this is with a top-down analysis of possible system failures, which involves evaluating the simplicity and probability of every attack on a system. This type of analysis is commonly referred to as an attack tree analysis.</li><li>Evaluate the probability of exploitation. Focus on the resources that are needed to create an attack, not the obscurity of a particular vulnerability. Be sure to account for technological advances. </li><li>Assume that people make mistakes. For example, end users might use a system improperly, compromising its security unintentionally.</li><li>Attackers might not use common and well-established techniques to compromise a system. Instead, they might hammer the system with seemingly random attacks, looking for possible information on how the system behaves under unexpected conditions.</li><li>Check all assumptions with other people. They might have a fresh perspective on potential threats and their probability. The more people that question the assumptions, the more likely a bad assumption will be identified.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009010200">
<title><content-text>Threat Identification and Risk Analysis</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9254326876">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010201/cm9254326876.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010201/cm9254326876text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>One of the first steps to establishing an organization's security needs is to identify likely threats. Threat identification provides an organization with a list of threats that a system is subject to in a particular environment. When identifying threats, it is important to ask two questions:</p> <p><ul><li>What are the possible vulnerabilities of a system?</li><li>What are the consequences if system vulnerabilities are exploited?</li></ul></p> <p>For example, threat identification for connecting an e-banking system would include:</p> <p><ul><li><b>Internal system compromise</b> - The attacker uses the exposed e-banking servers to break into an internal bank system.</li><li><b>Stolen customer data</b> - An attacker steals the personal and financial data of bank customers from the customer database.</li><li><b>Phony transactions from an external server - </b>An attacker alters the code of the e-banking application and runs arbitrary transactions impersonating a legitimate user.</li><li><b>Phony transactions if the customer PIN or smart card is stolen - </b>An attacker steals the identity of a customer and runs malicious transactions from the compromised account.</li><li><b>Insider attack on the system - </b>A bank employee finds a flaw in the system to mount an attack.</li><li><b>Data input errors - </b>A user inputs incorrect data or makes incorrect transaction requests. </li><li><b>Data center destruction - </b>A cataclysmic event severely damages or destroys the data center.</li></ul></p> <p>Identifying vulnerabilities on a network entails understanding the important applications that are used as well as the different vulnerabilities of that application and hardware. This can require a significant amount of research on the part of the network administrator.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6275821410">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010202/cm6275821410.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010202/cm6275821410text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Risk analysis is the systematic study of uncertainties and risks. It estimates the probability and severity of threats to a system and provides an organization with a prioritized list. Risk analysts identify the risks, determine how and when those risks might arise, and estimate the impact (financial or otherwise) of adverse outcomes. </p> <p>The first step in developing a risk analysis is to evaluate each threat to determine its severity and probability:</p> <p><ul><li><b>Internal system compromise</b> - Extremely severe and likely if untrusted software is used to pass data to the inside network.</li><li><b>Stolen customer data</b> - Severe and likely if the external server is vulnerable to intrusions, which could compromise the operating system or application.</li><li><b>Phony transactions if external server is broken into</b> - Severe and likely if the external server is vulnerable to intrusions, which could compromise the operating system or application.</li><li><b>Phony transactions if customer PIN or smart card is stolen - </b>Limited severity because individual accounts are compromised. Likely only if the stolen credentials are not detected quickly.</li><li><b>Insider attack on the system - </b>Extremely severe and likely based on past insider attacks on company data.</li><li><b>Data input errors</b> - Moderate severity and likely because of human error.</li><li><b>Data center destruction - </b>Extremely severe but not likely because it requires an event of epic proportions, such as a natural disaster.</li></ul></p> <p>After the threats are evaluated for severity and likelihood, the information is used in a risk analysis. There are two types of risk analysis in information security, quantitative and qualitative.</p> <p><b>Quantitative Risk Analysis</b></p> <p>Quantitative risk analysis uses a mathematical model that assigns a monetary figure to the value of assets, the cost of threats being realized, and the cost of security implementations. Monetary figures are typically based on an annual cost. </p> <p><b>Qualitative Risk Analysis </b></p> <p>There are various ways of conducting qualitative risk analysis. One method uses a scenario-based model. This approach is best for large cities, states, and countries because it is impractical to try to list all the assets, which is the starting point for any quantitative risk analysis. For example, by the time a typical national government lists all of its assets, the list would have hundreds or thousands of changes and would no longer be accurate.</p> <p>With qualitative risk analysis, research is exploratory and cannot always be graphed or proven mathematically. It focuses mostly on the understanding of why risk is present and how various solutions work to resolve the risk. Quantitative risk analysis is more mathematically precise and typically used by organizations as cost justification for proposed countermeasures. For this reason, the next topic investigates the specifics of building a quantitative risk analysis.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1703336282">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010203/cm1703336282.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010203/cm1703336282text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Quantitative Risk Analysis</b></p> <p>Quantitative analysis relies on specific formulas to determine the value of the risk decision variables. These include formulas that calculate the asset value (AV), exposure factor (EF), single loss expectancy (SLE), annualized rate of occurrence (ARO), and annualized loss expectancy (ALE).</p> <p><b>Asset Value</b></p> <p>The asset value includes the purchase price, the cost of deployment, and the cost of maintenance. In the instance of a database or a web server, the AV should also include the cost of development. AV is not an easy number to calculate.</p> <p><b>Exposure Factor</b></p> <p>The exposure factor is an estimate of the degree of destruction that could occur. For example, suppose water flooding is a possibility that could affect the e-banking data center. What is the likelihood that it could destroy the data center? Would the destruction be 60 percent, 80 percent, or 100 percent? The risk assessment team must evaluate all possibilities and then make a determination. Assuming that a backup copy of all media and data is stored offsite, the only losses are to the hardware and productivity. Therefore, a flood would have a 60 percent destruction factor.</p> <p>As another example, consider data entry errors, which are much less damaging than a flood. A single data entry error is most likely less than a fraction of a percent in exposure, or .001 percent.</p> <p><b>Single Loss Expectancy</b></p> <p>The single loss expectancy calculation represents the expected loss from a single occurrence of the threat. The SLE is defined as AV multiplied by EF. Using the previous examples, the SLE calculations result in the following:</p> <p><u>Flood threat</u></p> <p><ul><li>Exposure Factor is 60 percent </li><li>AV of the enterprise is US$10,000,000</li><li>SLE is US$10,000,000 * .60 = US$6,000,000</li></ul></p> <p><u>Data entry error</u></p> <p><ul><li>Exposure Factor is .001 percent</li><li>AV of data and databases is US$1,000,000 </li><li>SLE is US$1,000,000 * .000001 = US$10 </li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8242758023">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010204/cm8242758023.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010204/cm8242758023text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Annualized Rate of Occurrence</b></p> <p>The annualized rate of occurrence estimates the frequency of an event and is used to calculate the ALE.</p> <p>Using the previous examples, the type of flood to affect the data center would be a flood-of-the-century event, so it has a 1/100 chance of occurring this year, making the ARO for the flood 1/100.</p> <p>Expect a data entry error to occur 500 times a day. Because the organization is open for business 250 days per year, estimate the ARO for the data entry error to be 500 * 250, or 125,000 total occurrences.</p> <p><b>Annualized Loss Expectancy</b></p> <p>Risk analysts calculate the ALE in annualized terms to address the cost to the organization if the organization does nothing to counter existing threats. The ALE is derived from multiplying the SLE by the ARO. The ALE calculations for the examples are surprising.</p> <p><u>Flood threat</u></p> <p><ul><li>SLE is US$6,000,000</li><li>ARO is .01</li><li>ALE is US$6,000,000 * .01 = US$60,000</li></ul></p> <p><u>Data input error</u></p> <p><ul><li>SLE is US$10</li><li>ARO is 125,000</li><li>ALE is US$10 * 125,000 = US$1,250,000</li></ul></p> <p>A decision to spend US$50,000 to enhance the security of database applications to reduce data entry errors significantly is now an easy decision. It is equally easy to reject a proposal to enhance the defenses against floods that cost US$3,000,000.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010205">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5334257451">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010205/cm5334257451.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010200/en2009010205/cm5334257451text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>It is necessary to perform a quantitative risk analysis for all threats identified during the threat identification process. </p> <p>A list of all identified threats should state each expected issue, the relative cost of that issue, and the total cost if all expected threats are realized. This list should then be prioritized based on the most serious threat and relative cost. </p> <p>If an organization had a list of 10 expected threats, it could then prioritize the threats and address the most serious ones first. This prioritization enables management to focus resources where they do the most good. For example, suppose an organization compiled this list of threats and costs:</p> <p><ul><li>Insider network abuse - US$1,000,000 in lost productivity</li><li>Data input error - US$500,000</li><li>Worm outbreak - US$100,000</li><li>Viruses - US$10,000</li><li>Laptop theft - US$10,000</li></ul></p> <p>Assume that a current anti-virus solution is in place and decision makers must decide whether to update it. Based on quantitative analysis, decision makers could determine that resources are best used toward addressing insider network abuse and not toward the new anti-virus solution. </p> <p>In incidents that involve national security, it is not advisable to base decisions on cost.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009010300">
<title><content-text>Risk Management and Risk Avoidance</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3610128593">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010301/cm3610128593.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010301/cm3610128593text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When the threats are identified and the risks are assessed, a protection strategy must be deployed to protect against the risks. There are two very different methods to handle risks:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Risk management</b> - This method deploys protection mechanisms to reduce risks to acceptable levels. Risk management is perhaps the most basic and the most difficult aspect of building secure systems, because it requires a good knowledge of risks, risk environments, and mitigation methods.</li><li> <b>Risk avoidance</b> - This method eliminates risk by avoiding the threats altogether, which is usually not an option in the commercial world, where controlled, or managed, risk enables profits.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8223825043">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010302/cm8223825043.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010302/cm8223825043text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Consider the bank that wants to provide e-banking services. Risk management can be illustrated by high-level strategy decisions, which describe how to mitigate each risk. Keep in mind that not all mitigation techniques are implemented based on the risk versus cost formula used in the quantitative risk analysis:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Internal system compromise</b> - Provide the minimum necessary privileges to internal users to perform specific tasks, and use secure applications that minimizes inside access.</li><li> <b>Stolen customer data</b> - Keep all customer data on inside servers, and only transfer data to the outside on demand.</li><li> <b>Phony transactions if external server is broken into</b> - Allow only man-in-the-middle attacks on the external server, and design the external server application so that is does not allow arbitrary transactions to be called for any customer account.</li><li> <b>Phony transactions if customer PIN or smart card is stolen</b> - Use a quick refresh of revocation lists, and have a contract with the user that forces the user to assume responsibility for stolen token cards.</li><li> <b>Insider attack on the system</b> - Strictly limit inside access to the application, and provide strict auditing of all accesses from the inside.</li><li> <b>Data input error</b> - Enhance the security of database applications, and provide a redundant checking system to reduce data entry errors.</li><li> <b>Data center destruction</b> - Ensure that backups are kept off campus and that additional equipment is on hand. Enhance defenses against flooding by raising equipment off the ground and taking other precautions.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009010303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6084893414">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010303/cm6084893414.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009010000/en2009010300/en2009010303/cm6084893414text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Using the risk avoidance approach, a company would decide to not offer e-banking services at all because it is deemed too risky. Such an attitude might be valid for some military organizations, but is usually not an option in the commercial world. Organizations that can manage the risks are traditionally the most profitable.</p> <p>After an organization identifies threats, it performs the appropriate analysis. If they decide to manage the risk, the next step is to create a security solution.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009020000">
<title><content-text>Cisco Self-Defending Network</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009020100">
<title><content-text>Introducing the Cisco Self-Defending Network</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9675044608">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020101/cm9675044608.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020101/cm9675044608text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>In the past, threats from internal and external sources moved slowly, and it was easy to defend against them. Now, Internet worms spread across the world in a matter of minutes. Security systems, and the network itself, must react instantaneously. As the nature of threats to organizations continues to evolve, the defensive posture taken by network security professionals and managers must also evolve. However, it is important that the evolution of network security solutions does not introduce complexity.</p> <p>Complexity is one of the biggest enemies of security. Complexity makes it hard for the designer or administrator to predict how parts of the system will interact, and makes the system hard or impossible to analyze from a security perspective. Simplicity of design and implementation should therefore be one of the main goals of the designer. To meet complex security needs, consider using multiple, simple, and easy-to-verify mechanisms.</p> <p>Simplicity is beneficial for the end users of the system. If the end user does not understand the system adequately, the system can be compromised through unintentional misuse. One way to introduce simplicity is to disable all unnecessary services that a system offers. Disabling unnecessary services removes many potential attack possibilities. On an end-user device, this practice is known as the enforcement of least privilege. </p> <p>The concept of least privileges specifies that each subject, user, program, or host should have only the minimum necessary privileges to perform tasks. Having too many privileges allows end users to do more damage, whether intentional or unintentional, than would otherwise be possible. Least privilege also simplifies system analysis for possible flaws.</p> <p>In addition to disabling unnecessary services on host devices, simplicity also entails disabling unnecessary services and features on networking devices. This is known as hardening.</p> <p>Another way to simplify security is to help simplify end user functions. For example, if email must be encrypted when sent to external partners, the simplest solution is to use technology, such as a mail gateway, to automate email encryption. </p> <p>Finally, simplicity should be built into the security design. There are many security solution vendors. To help simplify the design, it is recommended that all security mechanisms come from a single vendor. The Cisco Self-Defending Network (SDN) is a comprehensive, end-to-end solution for network security.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2173898445">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020102/cm2173898445.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020102/cm2173898445text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A Cisco Self-Defending Network uses the network to identify, prevent, and adapt to threats. Unlike point-solution strategies, where products are purchased individually without consideration for which products work best together, a network-based approach is strategic and meets the current challenges and evolves the security capability to address new security threats.</p> <p>To enable its strategy, a Cisco Self-Defending Network has three key principles:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Integrate</b> - Security should be incorporated into the existing infrastructure. Security is built in, not bolted on.</li><li> <b>Collaborate</b> - Security services should work in partnership with existing network services to leverage the strengths of each area.</li><li> <b>Adapt</b> - The network should have the ability to intelligently evolve and adjust based on changing needs and emerging threats.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4886958689">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020103/cm4886958689.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020103/cm4886958689text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Self-Defending Network strategy starts with a strong, secure, and flexible network platform. Security services are then layered on top of this platform as needed. Several security services are available through the Cisco Self-Defending Network:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Threat control and containment</b> - Includes devices and services that limit the exposure to threats as well as the extent of damage to the network if threats are realized.</li><li> <b>Secure communications</b> - Includes devices and services that ensure the confidentiality and privacy of all sensitive communications, whether it is data communication, voice communication, or wireless communication. </li><li> <b>Operational control and policy management</b> - Includes a suite of tools that comprise a framework for scalable policy administration and enforcement that span security end-to-end.</li></ul></p> <p>Individual point solutions from a variety of vendors increase costs over time because of unplanned network design adjustments, inconsistencies, and complexities. The Cisco Self-Defending Network increases the value of an investment over time by using a common infrastructure. Management is more efficiently performed when it is simplified, enabling the identification and resolution of gaps before they become disabling vulnerabilities in the network design.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020104">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7264439958">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020104/cm7264439958.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020100/en2009020104/cm7264439958text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Cisco Self-Defending Network approach is comprehensive and includes the following tools to provide security services:</p> <p><ul><li> Cisco Security Manager provides policy-based management.</li><li> Cisco Security Monitoring, Analysis, and Response System (MARS) provides threat management.</li><li> Cisco IOS software, Cisco Adaptive Security Appliances, and Cisco Intrusion Prevention System (IPS) Sensor Software provide network security.</li><li> Cisco NAC appliances and Cisco Security Agent provide endpoint security.</li></ul></p> <p>There are a number of additional benefits that result from this comprehensive, integrated approach:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>360 degree visibility and protection</b> - Delivers comprehensive and proactive network defense. Infrastructure-wide threat intelligence is delivered cost-effectively across a variety of systems and devices. Multivector threat identification captures policy violations, vulnerability exploits, and anomalous behavior.</li><li> <b>Simplified control</b> - Streamlines network-wide policy management and infrastructure-wide implementation across a variety of systems and devices.</li><li> <b>Buisness resiliency</b> - Ensures the operations of the enterprise. Unparalleled collaboration and correlation across systems, endpoints, and management enables adaptive response to real-time threats. This is a vital element of the Cisco Self-Defending Network strategy.</li></ul></p> <p>This enhanced threat control and containment solution portfolio delivers comprehensive threat protection across the entire infrastructure ensuring business continuity.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009020200">
<title><content-text>Solutions for the Cisco SDN</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5169338867">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020201/cm5169338867.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020201/cm5169338867text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Threat Control and Containment</b></p> <p>The Cisco Threat Control and Containment solution protects the network, servers, endpoints, and information. It is enabled by behavioral-based endpoint protection, DDoS mitigation, intrusion prevention, network anti-virus, policy enforcement, and proactive response. It regulates network access, isolates infected systems, prevents intrusions, and protects critical business assets. The Cisco Threat Control and Containment counteracts malicious traffic such as worms, viruses, and malware before they affect business through the use of centralized policy, configuration, and threat event management.</p> <p>The Cisco Threat Control and Containment solution contains three elements:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Threat control for endpoints</b> - This element defends against threats most commonly introduced by Internet use, such as viruses, spyware, and other malicious content. Cisco products that provide threat control for endpoints include the Cisco Security Agent for Desktops, Cisco ASA 5500 Series Adaptive Security Appliances (Content Security Edition), Cisco Integrated Services Routers, Cisco IPS, and Cisco NAC appliance.</li><li> <b>Threat control for infrastructure</b> - This element safeguards the server and application infrastructure against attacks and intrusions. It also defends against internal and external attempts to penetrate or attack servers and information resources through application and operating system vulnerabilities. Products that provide threat control for the infrastructure include the Cisco Security Agent for Servers, Cisco IPS, Cisco firewall solutions including the ASA 5500 Series and Cisco Catalyst 6500 Series Firewall Services Module, Cisco Application Control Engine (ACE) Module, Cisco Application Velocity System (AVS), XML security, Cisco Security MARS, and Cisco Security Manager.</li><li> <b>Threat control for email</b> - This element protects business productivity, resource availability, and confidential information by stopping email initiated threats.</li></ul></p> <p>There are a number of benefits to the Cisco Threat Control and Containment solution:</p> <p><ul><li> Proactively protects against threats</li><li> Enforces endpoint compliance for more manageable patching and updating</li><li> Proactively contains infections and outbreaks with distributed mitigation</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1630052901">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020202/cm1630052901.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020202/cm1630052901text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Secure Communications</b></p> <p>Many organizations use the flexibility and cost effectiveness of the Internet to extend their network to branch offices, telecommuters, customers, and partners. When an organization extends its network in this way, ensuring the privacy and integrity of all information sent across the Internet is vital. This requires a manageable and cost-effective communications infrastructure that allows for secure communications. Secure communication is achieved through the use of IPsec and SSL VPNs.</p> <p>There are several benefits to implementing a secure communications infrastructure:</p> <p><ul><li> Improve business productivity and efficiency</li><li> Enable new business applications</li><li> Help comply with information privacy regulations</li></ul></p> <p>The Cisco Secure Communications solution is a set of security services. These services are essential to the Cisco Self-Defending Network. The secure communications solution has two major elements. Both use cryptography to ensure confidentiality:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Secure communications for remote access</b> - Provides highly secure, customizable access to corporate networks and applications by establishing an encrypted tunnel across the Internet.</li><li> <b>Secure communications for site-to-site connections</b> - Provides an Internet-based WAN infrastructure for connecting branch offices, home offices, or the sites of business partners to all or portions of a network.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8683356419">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020203/cm8683356419.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020203/cm8683356419text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Operational Control and Policy Management</b></p> <p>Operational control and policy management helps automate, simplify, and integrate a network to reduce operational costs and improve productivity. The Cisco Security Management Suite is a framework of products and technologies that are designed for scalable policy administration and enforcement for the Cisco Self-Defending Network. </p> <p>There are two components in the Cisco Security Management Suite: Cisco Security Manager and Cisco Security MARS. They work together to centrally manage the network and to achieve critical functions such as availability, responsiveness, resilience, and security in a consistent way. Cisco Security Manager and Cisco Security MARS were designed to complement CiscoWorks products. This integrated solution simplifies and automates the tasks that are associated with security management operations, including configuration, monitoring, analysis, and response.</p> <p>The Cisco Security Management Suite provides a number of benefits:</p> <p><ul><li>Increases speed and accuracy of policy deployment</li><li>Improves visibility to monitor end-to-end security </li><li>Provides more rapid response to threats </li><li>Enforces corporate policy compliance</li><li>Enhances proper workflow management</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6926472931">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020204/cm6926472931.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020204/cm6926472931text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Cisco Security Manager is a powerful, easy-to-use solution for centrally provisioning all aspects of device configurations and security policies for the Cisco family of security products. The solution is effective for managing even small networks consisting of fewer than 10 devices, but also scales for efficiently managing large-scale networks composed of thousands of devices. Scalability is achieved through intelligent policy-based management techniques that can simplify administration. Cisco Security Manager includes a number of features:</p> <p><ul><li> It supports provisioning for Cisco router platforms running a Cisco IOS Security Software image, including Cisco ASA 5500 Series Adaptive Security Appliances, Cisco PIX 500 Series Security Appliances, Cisco IPS 4200 Series Sensors, and Cisco Catalyst 6500 Series Advanced Inspection and Prevention Security Services Module (AIP-SSM).</li><li> It responds faster to threats by allowing an administrator to define and assign new security policies to thousands of devices in a few simple steps.</li><li> It has a rich graphical user interface (GUI) that provides ease of use.</li><li> Multiple views provide flexible methods to manage devices and policies, including the ability to manage the security network visually on a topology map.</li><li> It contains extensive animated help for the new user, which reduces learning time.</li><li> It allows an administrator to specify, centrally, which policies are shared and automatically inherited by new devices.</li><li> It integrates with Cisco Secure Access Control Server (ACS) for granular role-based access control to devices and management functions.</li><li> It integrates with Cisco Security MARS to correlate events with the associated firewall rules to make decisions faster and increase network uptime. </li><li> It provides the ability to assign specific tasks to each administrator during the deployment of a policy, with formal change control and tracking. This results in improved team coordination.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020205">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4990917722">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020205/cm4990917722.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020200/en2009020205/cm4990917722text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Cisco Security MARS provides security monitoring for network security devices and host applications made by Cisco and other providers. Cisco Security MARS offers these benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> Greatly reduces false positives by providing an end-to-end view of the network.</li><li> Defines the most effective mitigation responses by tracking the configuration and topology of the environment.</li><li> Promotes awareness of environmental anomalies with network behavior analysis using NetFlow.</li><li> Provides quick and easy access to audit compliance reports with more than 150 ready-to-use customizable reports. </li><li> Makes precise recommendations for threat removal, including the ability to visualize the attack path and identify the source of the threat with detailed topological graphs that simplify security response at Layer 2 and above.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009020300">
<title><content-text>Cisco Integrated Security Portfolio</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4500007129">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020300/en2009020301/cm4500007129.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020300/en2009020301/cm4500007129text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A truly secure network requires multiple products and technologies that collaborate seamlessly across platforms and integrate tightly with the network infrastructure. No single product or technology is able to secure a network. </p> <p>Cisco offers the broadest portfolio of integrated security products in the industry. The portfolio is designed to meet the requirements and diverse deployment models of any network and any environment. These integrated security products provide a comprehensive solution:</p> <p><ul><li> Cisco IOS platforms with integrated IPS, VPN, and stateful firewall to support secure IP connectivity</li><li> Cisco Adaptive Security Appliances with integrated VPN to ensure perimeter security, access control, and IPS</li><li> Cisco PIX Security Appliances with integrated VPN to ensure perimeter security and access control</li><li> Appliance-based network IDS and IPS and integrated network IDS and IPS for Cisco IOS routers, Cisco PIX Security Appliances, and Cisco ASA</li><li> Cisco Security Agent endpoint protection software to protect servers and desktops from the damaging effects of threats</li><li> Cisco Secure ACS to ensure that users have the proper authority to access corporate resources</li><li> Security modules for Cisco switches and Cisco routers that provide security throughout the data center</li><li> Security management products, including Cisco Security Manager, Cisco Security MARS, Cisco Router and Security Device Manager (SDM), and other GUI-based device managers</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009020302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7392357054">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020300/en2009020302/cm7392357054.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009020000/en2009020300/en2009020302/cm7392357054text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most organizations do not adopt all components of the Cisco Self-Defending Network at one time. This is because it can be difficult to overhaul all the required subsystems at once without disrupting the integrity of the IT services. Additionally, some organizations are hesitant to relinquish security controls to an automated system until they are confident that the system operates dependably. The Cisco Self-Defending Network design accommodates these concerns by providing products that can deploy independently of one another. Other product solutions can be added over time as confidence builds in the overall network security design.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009030000">
<title><content-text>Operations Security</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009030100">
<title><content-text>Introducing Operations Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1963701221">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030100/en2009030101/cm1963701221.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030100/en2009030101/cm1963701221text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>While the Cisco Self-Defending Network does increase the level of security, it cannot guarantee a completely invulnerable network. New types of attacks and advances in hacking technologies are still threats to even the most secure systems. Additionally, all networks are vulnerable to attack if the planning, implementation, operations, and maintenance of the network do not adhere to operational security practices. Operations security is concerned with the day-to-day practices necessary to first deploy and later maintain a secure system. </p> <p>Operations security starts with the planning and implementation process of a network. During these phases, the operations team proactively analyzes designs, identifies risks and vulnerabilities, and makes the necessary adaptations. After a network is set up, the actual operational tasks begin, including the continual day-to-day maintenance of the environment. These activities are regular in nature and enable the environment, systems, and applications to continue to run correctly and securely.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1148195707">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030100/en2009030102/cm1148195707.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030100/en2009030102/cm1148195707text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The responsibilities of the operations team pertain to everything that takes place to keep the network, computer systems, applications, and the environment up and running in a secure and protected manner. These individuals are concerned with the controls or security solutions used to protect hardware, software, and media on a day-to-day basis. This includes protection from threats in the operating environment, internal and external intruders, and operators who access resources inappropriately.</p> <p>The operations team usually has the objectives of preventing reoccurring problems, reducing hardware failures to an acceptable level, and reducing the impact of hardware failure or disruption. They should investigate any unusual or unexplained occurrences, unscheduled initial program loads, deviations from standards, and other abnormal conditions occurring on the network. While the people within operations are responsible for ensuring that systems are protected and continue to run in a predictable manner, it is important to note that management is responsible for the behavior and correction of personnel. For this reason, it is necessary that management work closely with the operations team to ensure the continued security of the network.</p> <p>To ensure a secure working environment within the operations department, certain core principles should be integrated into the day-to-day activities:</p> <p><ul><li>Separation of duties - Two-person control and dual operator</li><li>Rotation of duties</li><li>Trusted recovery - Failure preparation and system recovery</li><li>Change and configuration controls</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009030200">
<title><content-text>Principles of Operations Security</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2067965105">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030201/cm2067965105.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030201/cm2067965105text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Separation of Duties</b></p> <p>Separation (or segregation) of duties (SoD) is one of the main concepts of internal control and is the most difficult and sometimes the most costly control to achieve. SoD states that no single individual has control over two or more phases of a transaction or operation. Instead, responsibilities are assigned in a way that incorporates checks and balances. This makes a deliberate fraud more difficult to perpetrate because it requires a collusion of two or more individuals or parties.</p> <p>The term SoD is already well known in financial systems. These companies do not combine roles such as receiving checks, approving discounts, depositing cash, reconciling bank statements, and approving time cards. This helps to reduce the potential damage from the actions of one person. Similarly, IT departments should be organized in a way that achieves adequate separation of duties. There are two methods to accomplish this.</p> <p>The first method is known as the two-person control principle. It states that a task requires two individuals, and each is responsible for reviewing and approving the work of the other. In addition to providing accountability and reducing opportunities for fraud, this principle has the added benefit of reducing errors within configurations. Because of the overhead costs involved, this practice is usually limited to sensitive duties that are considered potential security risks.</p> <p>Another method of implementing SoD is the dual operator principle in which a task is broken down and each part of the task is assigned to a different individual. The task is not complete until both individuals complete their part. An example of the dual operator principle is a check that requires two signatures for the bank to accept it.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3207822180">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030202/cm3207822180.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030202/cm3207822180text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Rotation of Duties</b></p> <p>Rotation of duties, or job rotation, is a security measure in which individuals are given a specific assignment for a certain amount of time before moving to a new assignment. To successfully implement this principle, it is important that individuals have the training necessary to complete more than one job. </p> <p>Peer review is built into the practice of rotation of duties. For example, suppose that a job rotation scheme has five people rotating through five different roles during the course of a week. Peer review of work occurs whether or not it was intended. When five people do one job in the course of the week, each person is effectively reviewing the work of the others.</p> <p>In addition to providing security, rotation of duties also prevents boredom and gives individuals a greater breadth of exposure to the entire network operation. This creates a strong and flexible operations department because everyone is capable of doing multiple jobs. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9805953864">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030203/cm9805953864.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030203/cm9805953864text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Trusted Recovery</b></p> <p>One of the easiest ways to compromise a system is to make the system restart and gain control of it before all of its defenses are reloaded. For this reason, trusted recovery is an important principle of operations security. This principle states that systems fail at some point, so a process for recovery must be established. The most common way to prepare for failure is to back up data on a regular basis.</p> <p>Backing up data is standard practice in most IT departments. Keep in mind that many backup software programs use an account that bypasses file security. Therefore, individuals with the right to back up data can have access to files that they would not ordinarily be able to access. The same is true if those individuals who have the right to restore data.</p> <p>Security professionals propose that a secure backup program contain some of the following practices:</p> <p><ul><li>A junior staff member is responsible for loading blank media.</li><li>Backup software uses an account that is unknown to individuals to bypass file security.</li><li>A different staff member removes the backup media and securely stores it onsite while being assisted by another member of the staff.</li><li>A separate copy of the backup is stored off site and handled by a third staff member who is accompanied by another staff member. </li></ul></p> <p>One of the easiest ways for an attacker to obtain a password file (or any other data) is to get a copy of the backup tape because the backup tape is not always handled or stored very securely.</p> <p>Being prepared for system failure is also an important part of operations security:</p> <p><ul><li>Back up critical data on a regular basis</li><li>Evaluate who has access to the files to back them up and what kind of access they have</li><li>Secure the backup media</li></ul></p> <p>System recovery follows system failure. There are several examples of programs and applications that incorporate system recovery features: </p> <p><ul><li>Operating systems and applications that have single-user or safe mode.</li><li>The ability to recover files that were open at the time of the problem. The autosave process in many desktop applications is an example of this ability. Memory dumps that many operating systems perform upon system failure are also an example of this ability.</li><li>The ability to retain the security settings of a file after a system crash is critical so that the security is not bypassed by forcing a crash.</li><li>The ability to recover and retain security settings for critical system files such as the registry, configuration files, and password files.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009030204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2005461778">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030204/cm2005461778.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009030000/en2009030200/en2009030204/cm2005461778text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Configuration and Change Control</b></p> <p>Configuration and change control is a process that should be implemented to ensure that standardized methods and procedures are used to efficiently handle all changes. A change is defined as an event that results in a new status of one or more configuration items. A change should be approved by management, be cost effective, and be an enhancement to business processes with a minimum of risk to the IT infrastructure and security. </p> <p>The configuration and change controls should address three major components: the processes in place to minimize system and network disruption, backups and reversing changes that go badly, and guidance on the economic utilization of resources and time.</p> <p>A few suggestions are recommended to accomplish configuration changes in an effective and safe manner:</p> <p><ul><li>Ensure that the change is implemented in an orderly manner with formalized testing</li><li>Ensure that the end users are aware of the coming change when necessary</li><li>Analyze the effects of the change after it is implemented</li></ul></p> <p>Although the change control process differs from organization to organization, certain patterns emerge in change management. There are five steps in a typical change control process:</p> <p><b>Step 1.</b> Apply to introduce the change.</p> <p><b>Step 2.</b> Catalog the proposed change.</p> <p><b>Step 3.</b> Schedule the change.</p> <p><b>Step 4.</b> Implement the change.</p> <p><b>Step 5.</b> Report the change to the relevant parties.</p> <p>Operations security minimizes harm to the network by providing organized processes for security personnel. The effectiveness of an operations security solution fortunately can be tested without waiting for a real threat to take place. Network security testing makes this possible.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009040000">
<title><content-text>Network Security Testing</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009040100">
<title><content-text>Introducing Network Security Testing</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9751219383">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040101/cm9751219383.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040101/cm9751219383text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network security testing is testing that is performed on a network to ensure all security implementations are operating as expected. Typically, network security testing is conducted during the implementation and operational stages, after the system has been developed, installed, and integrated.</p> <p>Security testing provides insight into various administrative tasks such as risk analysis and contingency planning. It is important to document the results of security testing and make them available for staff involved in other IT areas. </p> <p>During the implementation stage, security testing is conducted on specific parts of the security system. </p> <p>After a network is fully integrated and operational, a Security Test and Evaluation (ST&amp;E) is performed. ST&amp;E is an examination or analysis of the protective measures that are placed on an operational network. </p> <p>Tests should be repeated periodically and whenever a change is made to the system. For security systems that protect critical information or protect hosts that are exposed to constant threat, security testing should be conducted more frequently.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6200992838">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040102/cm6200992838.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040102/cm6200992838text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>After a network is operational, it is important to ascertain its security status. Many tests can be conducted to assess the operational status of the system:</p> <p><ul><li>Network scanning</li><li>Vulnerability scanning</li><li>Password cracking</li><li>Log review</li><li>Integrity checkers</li><li>Virus detection</li><li>War dialing</li><li>War driving (802.11 or wireless LAN testing)</li><li>Penetration testing</li></ul></p> <p>Some testing techniques are predominantly manual and other tests are highly automated. Regardless of the type of testing, the staff that sets up and conducts the security testing should have significant security and networking knowledge, including expertise in the following areas: network security, firewalls, intrusion prevention systems (IPSs), operating systems, programming, and networking protocols, such as TCP/IP.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3079630194">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040103/cm3079630194.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040100/en2009040103/cm3079630194text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Network security testing results can be used in several ways:</p> <p><ul><li>As a reference point for corrective action</li><li>To define mitigation activities to address identified vulnerabilities</li><li>As a benchmark to trace the progress of an organization in meeting security requirements</li><li>To assess the implementation status of system security requirements</li><li>To conduct cost and benefit analysis for improvements to system security</li><li>To enhance other activities such as risk assessments, Certification and Authorization (C&amp;A), and performance improvement efforts</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009040200">
<title><content-text>Network Security Testing Tools</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7145583494">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040201/cm7145583494.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040201/cm7145583494text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>There are many tools available to test the security of systems and networks. Some of these tools are open source while others are commercial tools that require licensing.</p> <p>Two of the most common security testing tools are Nmap and SuperScan.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4642198158">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040202/cm4642198158.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040202/cm4642198158text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Nmap</b></p> <p>Nmap is the best-known low-level scanner available to the public. It is simple to use and has an array of excellent features which can be used for network mapping and reconnaissance. The basic functionality of Nmap allows the user to accomplish several tasks:</p> <p><ul><li> Classic TCP and UDP port scanning - looking for different services on one host. </li><li> Classic TCP and UDP port sweeping - looking for the same service on multiple hosts.</li><li> Stealth TCP and UDP port scans and sweeps - similar to classic scans and sweeps but harder to detect by the target host or IPS.</li><li> Remote operating system identification, known as OS fingerprinting.</li></ul></p> <p>Advanced features of Nmap include protocol scanning, known as Layer 3 port scanning. This feature identifies Layer 3 protocol support on a host. Examples of protocols that can be identified include GRE and OSPF. </p> <p>While Nmap can be used for security testing, it can also be used for malicious purposes. Nmap has an additional feature that allows it to use decoy hosts, on the same LAN as the target host, to mask the source of the scan. </p> <p>Nmap has no Application Layer features and runs on UNIX, Linux, Windows and OS X.</p> <p>Both console and graphical versions are available. The Nmap program and Zenmap GUI can be downloaded from the internet. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7136116571">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040203/cm7136116571.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040203/cm7136116571text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>SuperScan</b></p> <p>SuperScan is a Microsoft Windows port scanning tool. It runs on most versions of Windows and requires administrator privileges. Windows XP SP2 has removed support for raw sockets which limits the ability of SuperScan and other scanning tools.</p> <p>A raw socket is a socket that allows a user to directly access and manipulate the header of a data packet.</p> <p>While SP2 has increased the security aspect of this tool, some functionality can be restored by entering the <b>net stop SharedAccess</b> command at the Windows command prompt.</p> <p>SuperScan version 4 has a number of very useful features:</p> <p><ul><li>Adjustable scanning speed</li><li>Support for unlimited IP ranges</li><li>Improved host detection using multiple ICMP methods</li><li>TCP SYN scanning</li><li>UDP scanning (two methods)</li><li>Simple HTML report generation</li><li>Source port scanning</li><li>Fast hostname resolving</li><li>Extensive banner grabbing</li><li>Massive built-in port list description database</li><li>IP and port scan order randomization</li><li>A selection of useful tools (ping, traceroute, and whois)</li><li>Extensive Windows host enumeration capability</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009040204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm3442406894">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040204/cm3442406894.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009040000/en2009040200/en2009040204/cm3442406894text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Tools such as <b>Nmap</b> and <b>SuperScan</b> can provide effective penetration testing on a network and determine network vulnerabilities while helping to anticipate possible attack mechanisms. However network testing cannot prepare a network administrator for every security problem. </p> <p>The good news is that networks can recover from most security issues by adapting the security solution. The bad news is that prior to adapting the security solution it is possible for an attack to cause disruption and even catastrophic damage. Catastrophic damage is serious disruption to network services or complete destruction of data or network systems. Catastrophic damage can also be caused by a cataclysmic event. A business must have a plan in place to recover and remain in business in the event of serious disruption or network destruction.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009050000">
<title><content-text>Buisness Continuity Planning and Disaster Recovery</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009050100">
<title><content-text>Continuity Planning</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009050101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4459426421">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050100/en2009050101/cm4459426421.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050100/en2009050101/cm4459426421text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Business continuity planning addresses the continuing operations of an organization in the event of a disaster or prolonged service interruption that affects the mission of the organization. These plans address an emergency response phase, a recovery phase, and a return to normal operation phase. These phases should include a short to medium-term framework to continue the organizational operations. Each phase also identifies the responsibilities of personnel and the available resources during an incident.</p> <p>In reality, contingency and disaster recovery plans do not address every possible scenario or assumption. Rather, they focus on the events most likely to occur and identify an acceptable method of recovery. Periodically, the plans and procedures should be practiced to ensure that they are effective and well understood.</p> <p>For example, business continuity planning may address the following concerns:</p> <p><ul><li>Moving or relocating critical business components and people to a remote location while the original location is being repaired</li><li>Utilizing different channels of communication to deal with customers, shareholders, and partners until operations return to normal</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009050102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7328961690">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050100/en2009050102/cm7328961690.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050100/en2009050102/cm7328961690text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Disaster recovery is the process of regaining access to the data, hardware, and software necessary to resume critical business operations after a natural or human-induced disaster. It also includes plans for coping with the unexpected or sudden loss of key personnel. A disaster recovery plan is part of business continuity planning.</p> <p>After the events of September 11, 2001, when many companies lost irreplaceable data, the effort put into protecting data has changed. It is believed that some companies spend up to 25 percent of their IT budget on disaster recovery planning to avoid larger losses. Research indicates that of the companies that have had a major loss of computerized records, 43 percent never reopen, 51 percent close within two years, and only 6 percent remain in business.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009050200">
<title><content-text>Disruptions and Backups</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009050201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1325891093">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050200/en2009050201/cm1325891093.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050200/en2009050201/cm1325891093text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>When planning for disaster recovery and business continuity, the first step is identifying the possible types of disasters and disruptions. Not all disruptions to business operations are equal. A good disaster recovery plan takes into account the magnitude of the disruption, recognizing that there are differences between catastrophes, disasters, and minor incidents.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009050202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1454270004">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050200/en2009050202/cm1454270004.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009050000/en2009050200/en2009050202/cm1454270004text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The only way to deal with destruction is redundancy. When a component is destroyed, it must be replaced with a redundant component. This component can be a standby component that is owned by the organization for disaster recovery purposes or a new device that is provided by the service provider that the organization has contracted services with. If the service provider is responsible for providing redundant components, this information must be contained within the service level agreement (SLA). The SLA should also cover redundancy when service is disrupted or provide for some type of compensation. </p> <p>On a much larger scale, an organization might require a redundant facility if some catastrophic event results in facility destruction. Redundant facilities are referred to as hot, warm, and cold sites. </p> <p>Each type of facility is available for a different price with different resulting downtimes. With hot sites, a completely redundant facility is required with almost identical equipment. The copying of data to this redundant facility is part of normal operations, so in the case of a catastrophe, only the latest data changes must be applied to restore full operations. Organizations that need to respond in seconds often employ global load balancing (GLB) and distributed SANs to respond quickly. With this type of redundancy in place, an organization can quickly recover from disruption or even destruction . </p> <p>Warm sites are physically redundant facilities, but software and data are not stored and updated on the equipment. A disaster recovery team is required to physically go to the redundant facility and get it operational. Depending on how much software and data is involved, it can take days before operations are ready to resume.</p> <p>A cold site is usually an empty datacenter with racks, power, WAN links, and heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) already present, but no equipment. In this instance, an organization must first acquire routers, switches, firewalls, servers, and other equipment to rebuild everything. When the backups are uploaded onto the new equipment, operations can continue. This option is the least expensive in terms of money spent annually, but usually requires weeks to resume operations.</p> <p>The type of redundancy, whether it is standby equipment, SLA redundancy agreements, or facility redundancy requirements, is dependant on the types of disasters that an organization deems possible and the time sensitivity of critical data. The more redundancy options an organization puts in place, the higher the cost. However, not having backup plans and recovery options could result in lost revenue and lost customer trust. </p> <p>It is important to keep in mind that the disaster recovery plan and business continuity plan include not only the redundancy options but also all the steps and personnel required to implement the backup plan.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009060000">
<title><content-text>System Development Life Cycle</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009060100">
<title><content-text>Introducing the SDLC</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5940350121">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060100/en2009060101/cm5940350121.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060100/en2009060101/cm5940350121text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Business continuity and disaster recovery plans are ever-changing documents. They must be adjusted to changes in environment, equipment, and business needs. These changes not only affect continuity plans, but all aspects of network operations. Documentation should be maintained and updated regularly, and security needs should be continuously evaluated.</p> <p>Evaluating system changes and adjusting plans are all part of a system life cycle. Keep in mind that the term "system" can refer to a single device or a group of devices that operate together within a network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5240395644">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060100/en2009060102/cm5240395644.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060100/en2009060102/cm5240395644text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A general system development life cycle (SDLC) includes five phases:</p> <p>1. Initiation</p> <p>2. Acquisition and development</p> <p>3. Implementation</p> <p>4. Operation and maintenance</p> <p>5. Disposition</p> <p>When using the SDLC to design a network, each phase should include a minimum set of security requirements. This results in less expensive and more effective security as compared to adding security to an operational system after the fact. This purposeful inclusion of security in every phase of the life cycle is part of the secure network life cycle management process.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009060200">
<title><content-text>Phases of the SDLC</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8859770790">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060201/cm8859770790.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060201/cm8859770790text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Initiation</b></p> <p>These are the security tasks related to the initiation phase of the SDLC:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Security categorization</b> - Define three levels of potential impact on organizations or individuals if there is a breach of security: low, moderate, and high. Security categorization standards help organizations make the appropriate selection of security controls for their information systems.</li><li> <b>Preliminary risk assessment</b> - Initial description of the basic security needs of the system that defines the threat environment in which the system operates.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6234539250">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060202/cm6234539250.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060202/cm6234539250text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Acquisition and Development</b></p> <p>These are the security tasks related to the acquisition and development phase of the SDLC:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Risk assessment</b> - Identify the protection requirements for the system through a formal risk assessment process. This analysis builds on the risk assessment that was performed during the initiation phase, but is more in-depth and specific.</li><li> <b>Security functional requirements</b> - Analyze the operating necessities addressing the system security environment, the enterprise information security policy, and enterprise security architecture. </li><li> <b>Security assurance requirements - </b>Address the developmental activities that are required and the assurance evidence that is needed to produce the desired level of confidence that the information security is working correctly and effectively. The analysis, which is based on legal and functional security requirements, serves as the basis for determining how much and what kinds of assurance are required.</li><li> <b>Security cost considerations and reporting - </b>Determine how much of the development cost to attribute toward information security over the life cycle of the system. These costs include hardware, software, personnel, and training.</li><li> <b>Security planning - </b>Complete document of the agreed-upon security controls. The security plan also fully describes the information system and includes attachments or references to key documents that support the information security program of the organization. Examples of documents that support the information security program include, such as a configuration management plan, contingency plan, incident response plan, security awareness and training plan, rules of behavior, risk assessment, security test and evaluation results, system interconnection agreements, security authorizations and accreditations, and a plan of action and milestones.</li><li> <b>Security control development</b> - Ensure that the security controls that are described by the various security plan are designed, developed, and implemented. The security plans for information systems that are currently in operation might call for the development of additional security controls to supplement the controls that are already in place or the modification of selected controls that are deemed less than effective.</li><li> <b>Developmental security test and evaluation</b> - Ensure that security controls that are developed for a new information system are working properly and are effective. Some types of security controls, primarily those of a non-technical nature, cannot be tested and evaluated until the information system is deployed. These controls are typically management and operational controls.</li><li> <b>Other planning components</b> - Consider all the necessary components of the development process when incorporating security into the network life cycle. These components include the appropriate contract, the participation of all necessary functional groups within an organization, the participation of the certifier and accreditor, and the development and execution of the contracting plans and processes.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5251898122">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060203/cm5251898122.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060203/cm5251898122text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Implementation</b></p> <p>These are the security tasks related to the implementation phase of the SDLC:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Inspection and acceptance - </b>Validate and verify that the functionality that the specification describes is included in the deliverables.</li><li> <b>System integration</b> - Ensure that the system is integrated at the operational site where the information system is deployed. The security control settings and switches must be enabled in accordance with the vendor instructions and the available security implementation guidance.</li><li> <b>Security certification</b> - Use established verification techniques and procedures. This step gives organization officials confidence that the appropriate safeguards and countermeasures are in place. Security certification also uncovers and describes the known vulnerabilities in the information system.</li><li> <b>Security accreditation</b> - Provide the necessary security authorization to process, store, and transmit the information that is required. This authorization is granted by a senior organization official and is based on the verified effectiveness of security controls to some agreed-upon level of assurance and an identified residual risk to organization assets or operations.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6879738520">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060204/cm6879738520.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060204/cm6879738520text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Operations and Maintenance</b></p> <p>These are the security tasks related to the operations and maintenance phase of the SDLC:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Configuration management and control</b> - Consider the potential security impacts caused by specific changes to an information system or its surrounding environment. Configuration management and configuration control procedures are critical to establishing an initial baseline of hardware, software, and firmware components and subsequently controlling and maintaining an accurate inventory of any changes to the system.</li><li> <b>Continuous monitoring</b> - Ensure that controls continue to be effective through periodic testing and evaluation. Reporting the security status of the information system to the appropriate officials is an essential activity of a comprehensive information security program.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009060205">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7237954138">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060205/cm7237954138.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009060000/en2009060200/en2009060205/cm7237954138text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Disposition</b></p> <p>These are the security tasks related to the disposition phase of the SDLC:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Information preservation</b> - Retain information as necessary to conform to legal requirements and to accommodate future technology changes that can render the retrieval method obsolete.</li><li> <b>Media sanitization</b> - Ensure that data is deleted, erased, and written over, as necessary.</li><li> <b>Hardware and software disposal</b> - Dispose of hardware and software as directed by the information system security officer.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="" id="en2009070000">
<title><content-text>Developing a Comprehensive Security Policy</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009070100">
<title><content-text>Security Policy Overview</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2498046545">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070101/cm2498046545.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070101/cm2498046545text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The Secure Network Life Cycle is a process of assessment and reevaluation of equipment and security needs as the network changes. One of the important aspects of this ongoing evaluation is understanding which assets an organization must protect, even as those assets are changing. </p> <p>Determine what the assets of an organization are by asking questions:</p> <p><ul><li> What does the organization have that others want?</li><li> What processes, data, or information systems are critical to the organization?</li><li> What would stop the organization from doing business or fulfilling its mission?</li></ul></p> <p>The answers might identify assets such as critical databases, vital applications, important customer and employee information, classified commercial information, shared drives, email servers, and web servers.</p> <p>Network security systems help protect these assets, but a security system alone cannot prevent assets from being vulnerable to threat. Technical, administrative, and physical security systems can all be defeated if the end user community does not adhere to security policies and procedures. </p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070102">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9028862368">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070102/cm9028862368.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070102/cm9028862368text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>A security policy is a set of security objectives for a company, rules of behavior for users and administrators, and system requirements. These objectives, rules, and requirements collectively ensure the security of a network and the computer systems in an organization. Much like a continuity plan, a security policy is a constantly evolving document based on changes in technology, business, and employee requirements. </p> <p>A comprehensive security policy has a number of benefits:</p> <p><ul><li> Demonstrates an organization's commitment to security.</li><li> Sets the rules for expected behavior.</li><li> Ensures consistency in system operations, software and hardware acquisition and use, and maintenance.</li><li> Defines the legal consequences of violations.</li><li> Gives security staff the backing of management.</li></ul></p> <p>Security policies are used to inform users, staff, and managers of an organization's requirements for protecting technology and information assets. A security policy also specifies the mechanisms that are needed to meet security requirements and provides a baseline from which to acquire, configure, and audit computer systems and networks for compliance. </p> <p>One of the most common security policy components is an acceptable (or appropriate) use policy (AUP). This component defines what users are allowed and not allowed to do on the various system components. This includes the type of traffic that is allowed on the network. The AUP should be as explicit as possible to avoid misunderstanding. For example, an AUP might list specific websites, newsgroups, or bandwidth intensive applications that are prohibited from being accessed by company computers or from the company network.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070103">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5222697156">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070103/cm5222697156.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070100/en2009070103/cm5222697156text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The audience for the security policy is anyone who has access to the network. The internal audience includes various personnel, such as managers and executives, departments and business units, technical staff, and employees. The external audience is also a varied group that includes partners, customers, suppliers, consultants, and contractors. It is likely that one document cannot meet the needs of the entire audience of a large organization. The goal is to ensure that the various information security policy documents are consistent with the needs of the intended audience.</p> <p>The audience determines the content of the policy. For example, it is probably unnecessary to include a description of why something is necessary in a policy that is intended for the technical staff. It can be assumed that the technical staff already knows why a particular requirement is included. Managers are not likely to be interested in the technical aspects of why a particular requirement is needed. Instead, they want a high-level overview or the principles supporting the requirement. Employees often require more information on why particular security rules are necessary. If they understand the reasons for the rules, they are more likely to comply with them.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070200">
<title><content-text>Structure of a Security Policy</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070201">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6792140515">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070201/cm6792140515.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070201/cm6792140515text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Most corporations use a suite of policy documents to meet their wide and varied needs. These documents are often broken into a hierarchical structure:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Governing policy</b> - High-level treatment of the security guidelines that are important to the entire company. Managers and technical staff are the intended audience. The governing policy controls all security-related interactions among business units and supporting departments in the company. </li><li> <b>Technical policy</b> - Used by security staff members as they carry out security responsibilities for the system. These policies are more detailed than the governing policy and are system-specific or issue-specific. For example, access control and physical security issues are described in a technical policy. </li><li> <b>End-user policy</b> - Covers all security topics that are important to end users. End users can include employees, customers, and any other individual user of the network.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070202">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9687215209">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070202/cm9687215209.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070202/cm9687215209text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Governing Policy</b></p> <p>The governing policy outlines the company's overall security goals for managers and technical staff. It covers all security-related interactions among business units and supporting departments in the company.</p> <p>The governing policy aligns closely with existing company policies and is placed at the same level of importance as these other policies. This includes human resource policies and other policies that mention security-related issues, such as email, computer use, or related IT subjects.</p> <p>A governing policy includes several components:</p> <p><ul><li> Statement of the issue that the policy addresses</li><li> How the policy applies in the environment</li><li> Roles and responsibilities of those affected by the policy</li><li> Actions, activities, and processes that are allowed and those that are not</li><li> Consequences of noncompliance</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070203">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6012562021">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070203/cm6012562021.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070203/cm6012562021text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Technical Policy</b></p> <p>Technical policies are detailed documents that are used by technical staff in the conduct of their daily security responsibilities. These policies are system-specific or issue-specific, such as router security and physical security issues. They are essentially security handbooks that describe what the technical staff does, but not how they perform the functions.</p> <p>Technical policies are broken down into specified technical areas, including: </p> <p><ul><li>General</li><li>Email </li><li>Remote access </li><li>Telephony </li><li>Application usage</li><li>Network usage</li><li>Wireless communication</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070204">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm5909755788">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070204/cm5909755788.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070200/en2009070204/cm5909755788text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>End User Policy</b></p> <p>End-user policies cover all rules pertaining to information security that end users should know about and follow. End-user policies might overlap with technical policies. These policies are generally grouped together into a single document for ease of use. </p> <p>Several different target groups require end-user policies. Each group might have to agree to a different end-user policy. For example, an employee end-user policy would probably be different from a customer end-user policy. </p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070300">
<title><content-text>Standards, Guidelines, and Procedures</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070301">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1131265438">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070301/cm1131265438.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070301/cm1131265438text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>The security policy documents are high-level overview documents. The security staff uses detailed documents to implement the security policies. These include the standards, guidelines, and procedures documents. </p> <p>Standards, guidelines, and procedures contain the actual details defined in the policies. Each document serves a different function, covers different specifications, and targets a different audience. Separating these documents makes it is easier to update and maintain them.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070302">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm1598781896">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070302/cm1598781896.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070302/cm1598781896text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Standards Documents</b></p> <p>Standards help an IT staff maintain consistency in the operations of the network. Standards documents include the technologies that are required for specific uses, hardware and software versioning requirements, program requirements, and any other organizational criteria that must be followed. This helps IT staff improve efficiency and simplicity in design, maintenance, and troubleshooting.</p> <p>One of the most important security principles is consistency. For this reason it is necessary for organizations to establish standards. Each organization develops standards to support its unique operating environment. For example, if an organization supports 100 routers, it is important that all 100 routers are configured using the established standards. Device configuration standards are defined in the technical section of an organization's security policy.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070303">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm2347346042">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070303/cm2347346042.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070303/cm2347346042text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Guideline Documents</b></p> <p>Guidelines provide a list of suggestions on how to do things better. They are similar to standards, but are more flexible and are not usually mandatory. Guidelines can be used to define how standards are developed and to guarantee adherence to general security policies. </p> <p>Some of the most helpful guidelines are found in organizational repositories called best practices. In addition to an organization's defined best practices, a number of guidelines are widely available:</p> <p><ul><li> National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) Computer Security Resource Center</li><li> National Security Agency (NSA) Security Configuration Guides</li><li> The Common Criteria standard</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070304">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9380003510">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070304/cm9380003510.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070300/en2009070304/cm9380003510text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Procedure Documents</b></p> <p>Procedure documents are longer and more detailed than standards and guidelines. Procedure documents include implementation details, usually with step-by-step instructions and graphics. Procedure documents are extremely important for large organizations to have the consistency of deployment that is necessary for a secure environment.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070400">
<title><content-text>Roles and Responsibilities</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070401">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4592370386">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070400/en2009070401/cm4592370386.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070400/en2009070401/cm4592370386text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>All persons in an organization, from the chief executive officer (CEO) to the newest hires, are considered end users of the network and must abide by the organization's security policy. Developing and maintaining the security policy is delegated to specific roles within the IT department. </p> <p>Executive-level management must always be consulted during security policy creation to ensure that the policy is comprehensive, cohesive, and legally binding. Smaller organizations might have a single executive position that oversees all aspects of operation, including network operations. Larger organizations might break up the executive task into several positions. The business and reporting structure of an organization depends on the organization's size and industry.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070402">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm8625754493">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070400/en2009070402/cm8625754493.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070400/en2009070402/cm8625754493text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Some of the more common executive titles include:</p> <p><ul><li> <b>Chief Executive Officer (CEO)</b> - Is ultimately responsible for the success of an organization. All executive positions report to the CEO.</li><li> <b>Chief technology officer (CTO)</b> - Identifies and evaluates new technologies and drives new technology development to meet organization objectives. Maintains and enhances the current enterprise systems, while providing direction in all technology-related issues in support of operations. </li><li> <b>Chief information officer (CIO)</b> - Responsible for the information technology and computer systems that support enterprise goals, including successful deployment of new technologies and work processes. Small- to medium-sized organizations typically combine the responsibilities of CTO and CIO into a single position that can use either title. When an organization has both a CTO and CIO, the CIO is generally responsible for processes and practices supporting the flow of information, and the CTO is responsible for technology infrastructure.</li><li> <b>Chief security officer (CSO)</b> - Develops, implements, and manages the organization's security strategy, programs, and processes associated with all aspects of business operation, including intellectual property. A major aspect of this position is to limit exposure to liability in all areas of financial, physical, and personal risk. </li><li> <b>Chief information security officer (CISO)</b> - Similar to the CSO, except that this position has a specific focus on IT security. One of the major responsibilities of the CISO is developing and implementing the security policy. The CISO might choose to be the primary author of the security policy or to delegate some or all of the authoring. In either case, the CISO is responsible and accountable for security policy content.</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070500">
<title><content-text>Security Awareness and Training</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070501">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7654547905">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070501/cm7654547905.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070501/cm7654547905text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Technical, administrative, and physical security is easily breached if the end-user community is not purposefully abiding security policies. To help ensure the enforcement of the security policy, a security awareness program must be put in place. Leadership must develop a program that keeps everyone aware of security issues and educates staff on how to work together to maintain the security of their data.</p> <p>A security awareness program reflects the business needs of an organization tempered by known risks. It informs users of their IT security responsibilities and explains the rules of behavior for using the IT systems and data within a company. This program must explain all IT security policies and procedures. A security awareness program is crucial to the financial success of any organization. It disseminates the information that all end users need to effectively conduct business in a way that protects the organization from loss of intellectual capital, critical data, and even physical equipment. The security awareness program also details the sanctions that the organization imposes for noncompliance. This portion of the program should be part of all new hire orientation.</p> <p>A security awareness program usually has two major components: </p> <p><ul><li> Awareness campaigns </li><li> Training and education</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070502">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9827649663">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070502/cm9827649663.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070502/cm9827649663text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Awareness Campaigns</b></p> <p>Awareness campaigns are usually aimed at all levels of the organization, including executive positions.</p> <p>Security awareness efforts are designed to change behavior or reinforce good security practices. Awareness is defined in NIST Special Publication 800-16 as: <i>"Awareness is not training. The purpose of awareness presentations is simply to focus attention on security. Awareness presentations are intended to allow individuals to recognize IT security concerns and respond accordingly. In awareness activities, the learner is the recipient of information... Awareness relies on reaching broad audiences with attractive packaging techniques."</i></p> <p>An example of a topic for an awareness session (or awareness material to be distributed) is virus protection. The subject can be briefly addressed by describing what a virus is, what can happen if a virus infects a user system, what the user must do to protect the system, and what users do if they discover a virus.</p> <p>There are several methods of increasing security awareness:</p> <p><ul><li> Lectures, videos</li><li> Posters, newsletter articles, and bulletins</li><li> Awards for good security practices</li><li> Reminders, such as login banners, mouse pads, coffee cups, and notepads</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070503">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6445138816">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070503/cm6445138816.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070503/cm6445138816text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Training and Education</b></p> <p>Training strives to impart needed security skills to end users who may or may not be members of the IT staff. The most significant difference between training and awareness is that training teaches skills that allow a person to perform a specific task, while awareness campaigns simply focus an individual's attention on security issues. The skills that users acquire during training build upon the information learned in security awareness campaigns. Following a security awareness campaign with training targeted to specific audiences helps cement the information and skills imparted. A training curriculum does not necessarily lead to a formal degree from an institution of higher learning, but it might contain much of the same material found in a course that a college or university includes in a certificate or degree program.</p> <p>An example of a training course for non-IT personnel is one that addresses appropriate security practices specific to those applications that the end user must use, such as database applications. An example of training for IT personnel is an IT security course that addresses in detail the management, operational, and technical controls that must be implemented. </p> <p>An effective security training course requires proper planning, implementation, maintenance, and periodic evaluation. The life cycle of a security training course includes several steps:</p> <p><b>Step 1. Id</b><b>entify course scope, goals, and objectives.</b> The scope of the course provides training to all types of people who interact with IT systems. Because users need training that relates directly to their use of particular systems, it is necessary to supplement a large organization-wide program by more system-specific courses.</p> <p><b>Step 2. Id</b><b>entify and educate training staff.</b> It is important that trainers have sufficient knowledge of computer security issues, principles, and techniques. It is also vital that they know how to communicate information and ideas effectively.</p> <p><b>Step 3. Id</b><b>entify target audiences.</b> Not everyone needs the same degree or type of computer security information to perform an assigned job. Security training courses that present only the information that is needed by the particular audience and omit irrelevant information have the best results.</p> <p><b>Step 4. M</b><b>otivate management and employees.</b> Consider using motivational techniques to show management and employees how their participation in a training course benefits the organization.</p> <p><b>Step 5. </b><b>Administer the courses.</b> Important considerations for administering the course include selecting appropriate training methods, topics, materials, and presentation techniques.</p> <p><b>Step 6. </b><b>Maintain the courses.</b> Stay informed of changes in computer technology and security requirements. Training courses that meet the needs of an organization today can become ineffective when the organization starts to use a new application or changes its environment, such as the deployment of VoIP. </p> <p><b>Step 7. </b><b>Evaluate the courses.</b> An evaluation seeks to ascertain how much information is retained, to what extent computer security procedures are being followed, and the general attitude toward computer security.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070504">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9431476979">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070504/cm9431476979.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070500/en2009070504/cm9431476979text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Education integrates all the security skills and competencies of the various functional specialties into a common body of knowledge, adds a multidisciplinary study of concepts, issues, and principles (technological and social), and strives to produce IT security specialists and professionals capable of vision and proactive response.</p> <p>An example of an educational program is a degreed program at a college or university. Some people take a course or several courses to develop or enhance their skills in a particular discipline. This is training as opposed to education. Many colleges and universities offer certificate programs, in which a student can take two or more classes in a related discipline and be awarded a certificate upon completion. Often, these certificate programs are conducted as a joint effort between schools and software or hardware vendors. These programs are more characteristic of training than education. Those responsible for security training must assess both types of programs and decide which one better addresses the identified needs.</p> <p>A successfully implemented security awareness program measurably reduces unauthorized actions by insiders, increases the effectiveness of existing controls, and helps fight waste, fraud, and abuse of information systems resources.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070600">
<title><content-text>Laws and Ethics</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070601">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm9220553053">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070600/en2009070601/cm9220553053.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070600/en2009070601/cm9220553053text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>Laws</b></p> <p>For many businesses today, one of the biggest considerations for setting security policies and implementing awareness programs is compliance with the law. Network security professionals must be familiar with the laws and codes of ethics that are binding on Information Systems Security (INFOSEC) professionals. Most countries have three types of laws: criminal, civil (also called tort), and administrative. </p> <p>Criminal law is concerned with crimes, and its penalties usually involve fines or imprisonment, or both. </p> <p>Civil law focuses on correcting situations in which entities have been harmed and an economic award can help. Imprisonment is not possible in civil law. An example of a civil law case is if one company sues another company for infringing on a patent. The penalty in civil law is usually monetary, although there can also be performance requirements such as ceasing to infringe on the patent. </p> <p>Administrative law involves government agencies enforcing regulations. For example, a company might owe its employees vacation pay. An administrative court could force the company to pay its employees as well as levy a fine that is payable to the court. </p> <p>Not all governments accept or classify their laws the same way. This can impede prosecution for computer and networking crimes that cross international boundaries.</p> <p><b>Ethics</b></p> <p>Ethics is a standard that is higher than the law. It is a set of moral principles that govern civil behavior. Ethical principles are often the foundation of many of the laws currently in place. These principles are frequently formalized into codes of ethics. Individuals that violate the code of ethics can face consequences such as loss of certification, loss of employment, and even prosecution by criminal or civil court. The information security profession has a number of formalized codes:</p> <p><ul><li> International Information Systems Security Certification Consortium, Inc (ISC)2 Code of Ethics</li><li> Computer Ethics Institute (CEI)</li><li> Internet Activities Board (IAB)</li><li> Generally Accepted System Security Principles (GASSP)</li></ul></p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070602">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7442249780">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070600/en2009070602/cm7442249780.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070600/en2009070602/cm7442249780text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p><b>(ISC)2 Code of Ethics </b></p> <p>The (ISC)2 code of ethics consists of the preamble and the ethics canons. The canons are explained in more detail at the (ISC)2 website.</p> <p><u>Code of Ethics Preamble</u></p> <p>Safety of the commonwealth, duty to our principals, and to each other requires that we adhere, and be seen to adhere, to the highest ethical standards of behavior. Therefore, strict adherence to this Code is a condition of certification.</p> <p><u>Code of Ethics Canons</u></p> <p> </p> <p><ul><li> Protect society, the commonwealth, and the infrastructure.</li><li> Act honorably, honestly, justly, responsibly, and legally.</li><li> Provide diligent and competent service to principals.</li><li> Advance and protect the profession.</li></ul></p> <p><b>Computer Ethics Institute Code of Ethics</b></p> <p>The CEI formalized its code of ethics as the Ten Commandments of Computer Ethics:</p> <p>1. Thou shalt not use a computer to harm other people.</p> <p>2. Thou shalt not interfere with other people's computer work.</p> <p>3. Thou shalt not snoop around in other people's computer files.</p> <p>4. Thou shalt not use a computer to steal.</p> <p>5. Thou shalt not use a computer to bear false witness.</p> <p>6. Thou shalt not copy or use proprietary software which is not paid for.</p> <p>7. Thou shalt not use other people's computer resources without authorization or proper compensation.</p> <p>8. Thou shalt not appropriate other people's intellectual output.</p> <p>9. Thou shalt think about the social consequences of the program being written or the system being designed.</p> <p>10. Thou shalt always use a computer in ways that ensure consideration and respect for fellow humans.</p> <p><b>IAB Code of Ethics</b></p> <p>The IAB issued a statement that constitutes its code of ethics:</p> <p>The Internet is a national facility whose utility is largely a consequence of its wide availability and accessibility. Irresponsible use of this critical resource poses an enormous threat to its continued availability to the technical community. The U.S. government, sponsors of this system, suffers when highly disruptive abuses occur. Access to and use of the Internet is a privilege and should be treated as such by all users of this system. The IAB strongly endorses the view of the Division Advisory Panel of the National Science Foundation Division of Network, Communications Research and Infrastructure which, in paraphrase, characterized as unethical and unacceptable any activity which purposely:</p> <p><ul><li> Seeks to gain unauthorized access to the resources of the Internet</li><li> Disrupts the intended use of the Internet</li><li> Wastes resources, such as people, capacity, and computer, through such actions</li><li> Destroys the integrity of computer-based information</li><li> Compromises the privacy of users</li></ul></p>  <p><b>GASSP Code of Ethics</b></p> <p>The GASSP Code of Ethics states that information systems and the security of information systems should be provided and used in accordance with the Code of Ethical Conduct of information security professionals. The Code of Ethical Conduct prescribes the relationships of ethics, morality, and information. </p> <p>As social norms for using IT systems evolve, the Code of Ethical Conduct will change and information security professionals will spread the new concepts throughout their organizations and products. Safeguards may require an ethical judgment for use or to determine limits or controls. For example, entrapment is a process for luring someone into performing an illegal or abusive act. As a security safeguard, a security professional might set up an easy-to-compromise hole in the access control system, and then monitor attempts to exploit the hole. This form of entrapment is useful in providing warning that penetration has occurred. It can also provide enough information to identify the perpetrator. Due to laws, regulations, or ethical standards, it may be unethical to use data that is collected via entrapment in prosecution, but it may be ethical to use entrapment as a detection and prevention strategy. One should seek both legal and ethical advice when designing network security.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
<topic type="" id="en2009070700">
<title><content-text>Responsing to a Security Breach</content-text></title>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070701">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm6550660101">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070700/en2009070701/cm6550660101.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070700/en2009070701/cm6550660101text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Laws and codes of ethics are in place to allow organizations and individuals a means of reclaiming lost assets and preventing crimes. Different countries have different legal standards. In most countries and courts, to successfully prosecute an individual, it is necessary to establish motive, opportunity, and means. </p> <p>Motive answers the question of why a person committed the illegal act. As a crime is investigated, it is important to start with individuals who might have been motivated to commit the crime. For example, employees who believe they were wrongly passed over for advancement may be motivated to sell confidential company data to a competitor. Having identified likely suspects, the next thing to consider is whether the suspects had the opportunity to commit the crime.</p> <p>Opportunity answers the question of when and where the person committed the crime. For example, if it can be established that three of the suspects were all participating in a wedding at the time of the security breach, they might have been motivated, but they did not have the opportunity because they were busy doing something else.</p> <p>Means answers the question of how the person committed the crime. It is pointless to accuse someone who does not have the knowledge, skills, or access to accomplish the crime. </p> <p>While establishing motive, opportunity, and means is a standard for finding and prosecuting individuals of all types of crimes, in computer crimes, it is fairly easy to manipulate and cover up evidence because of the complexity of computer systems, global accessibility via the Internet, and the knowledge of many attackers. For this reason, it is necessary to have strict protocols in place for security breaches. These protocols should be outlined in an organizations security policy.</p></content-text>
</page>
<page type="OneColumn" id="en2009070702">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm4181071310">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070700/en2009070702/cm4181071310.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009070000/en2009070700/en2009070702/cm4181071310text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text><p>Computer data is virtual data, meaning that there are rarely physical, tangible representations. For this reason, data can be easily damaged or modified. When working with computer data as part of a forensics case, the integrity of the data must be maintained if it is to be used as evidence in a court of law. For example, changing a single bit of data can change a timestamp from August 2, 2001 to August 3, 2001. A perpetrator can easily adjust data to establish a false alibi. Therefore, strict procedures are required to guarantee the integrity of forensics data recovered as part of an investigation. Some of the procedures that must be established are proper data collection, data chain of custody, data storage, and data backups.</p> <p>The process of collecting data must be done precisely and quickly. When a security breach occurs, it is necessary to isolate the infected system immediately. Systems should not be shut down or rebooted before the memory is dumped to a file because the system flushes the memory every time a device is powered off. Additionally, a drive image should be taken before working with data on the hard drive. Multiple copies of the hard drive are usually made after the device is powered down to establish master copies. These master copies are usually locked up in a safe, and investigators use working copies for both the prosecution and the defense. Investigators can determine if data tampering has occurred by comparing working copies to the master copy that has been secured and untouched since the beginning of the investigation.</p> <p>After data is collected but before equipment is disconnected, it is necessary to photograph the equipment in place. All evidence must be handled while maintaining a proper chain of custody, meaning that only those individuals with authorization have access to evidence, and all access is documented. </p> <p>If security protocols are established and followed, organizations can minimize the loss and damages resulting from attacks.</p></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
<section type="ChapterSummary" id="en2009080000">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<topic type="" id="en2009080100">
<title><content-text>Chapter Summary</content-text></title>
<page type="FullScreen" id="en2009080101">
<content-media type="StaticGraphic" id="cm7796074456">	<title><content-text></content-text></title>	<media ref="en2009000000/en2009080000/en2009080100/en2009080101/cm7796074456.swf" mime="shockwave/flash" scale="true" type="file" width="400" height="200" external="en2009000000/en2009080000/en2009080100/en2009080101/cm7796074456text.xml"/></content-media>
<content-text></content-text>
</page>
</topic>
</section>
</chapter>
